<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of Christianity laying open the abuses thereof in the anti-Christian lives and worship of many of its professors, especially the Romanists : and shewing the way to a holy life in the character of a true Christian / written originally in French by the famous Monsieur de Gombaud ; and now done into English by P Lorrain.</title>
            <author>Gombauld, Jean Ogier de, d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41383</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1023</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14522</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11845155</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11845155</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49820</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41383)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49820)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 532:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of Christianity laying open the abuses thereof in the anti-Christian lives and worship of many of its professors, especially the Romanists : and shewing the way to a holy life in the character of a true Christian / written originally in French by the famous Monsieur de Gombaud ; and now done into English by P Lorrain.</title>
                  <author>Gombauld, Jean Ogier de, d. 1666.</author>
                  <author>Lorrain, P. (Paul), d. 1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 162 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for S. Lowndes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49820:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49820:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF Chriſtianity: Laying Open The <hi>Abuſes</hi> thereof in the <hi>ANTI-CHRISTIAN LIVES</hi> and <hi>WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIP</hi> of many of its <hi>Profeſſors; Eſpecially, the</hi> ROMANISTS; AND Shewing the WAY to a HOLY LIFE in the CHARACTER of a <hi>True Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written Originally in</hi> French <hi>by the Famous Monſieur</hi> de Gombaud. <hi>And now done into</hi> Engliſh <hi>by</hi> P. Lorrain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>S. Lowndes,</hi> over againſt <hi>Exeter Exchange</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:49820:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>October <hi>14. 1692.</hi>
               </date>
               <signed>Ra. Barker R. in Chriſto Patri ac D. Dom. Johan. Arch. a Sacris Dom.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49820:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>WILLIAM</hi> Earl of <hi>DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VONSHIRE,</hi> Baron <hi>Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of the Counties of <hi>Derby</hi> and <hi>Nottingham,</hi> Lord Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of <hi>HIS MAJESTY's</hi> Houſhold, Knight of the Moſt Noble Order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> and One of <hi>THEIR MAJESTIES</hi> Moſt Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Privy Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <hi>May it pleaſe</hi> YOUR LORDSHIP,</opener>
            <p>HAving no other way publickly to expreſs my grateful Senſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:49820:3"/>deep Obligations, laid by YOUR LORDSHIP upon my Family, and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar upon my ſelf, I am prompted to do it by this <hi>Dedication.</hi> Wherein yet I dare not undertake (as it is uſual on ſuch Occaſions) to delineate YOUR LORD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIP's High Character, and (though perhaps I might do it without ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Flattery) fall upon the <hi>Encomium</hi> of Your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Virtues, and Eminent Actions; partly, becauſe they are ſo univerſally known already to the World, as not to need the Pen of any
<pb facs="tcp:49820:3"/>
               <hi>Panegyriſt,</hi> much leſs ſuch an one as mine, who reckon my ſelf inſufficient for ſo great a Task; And partly, becauſe I believe YOUR LORDSHIP would not like the Way that is ſo common and ſo much abus'd. Only I hope it may not be thought below YOUR GRAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEUR to patronize this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Piece (at leaſt for the <hi>Subject,</hi> and the <hi>Author</hi>'s ſake) and to bear with what faults Your Judicious Eye ſhall find in the <hi>Tranſlator,</hi> who humbly begs Pardon for this preſumption, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts it a great Honour
<pb facs="tcp:49820:4"/>to be known and own'd by YOUR LORDSHIP, as</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute> 
               <signed>YOUR LORDSHIP's <hi>Moſt Humbly Devoted and Moſt Obedient Servant,</hi> PAUL LORRAIN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49820:4"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THough it would be ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to offer any thing in Commendation of this ſmall <hi>TREATISE,</hi> to ſuch as have read it in its <hi>Native</hi> Language, or been acquainted with the <hi>Worth</hi> of its <hi>Author, Monſieur de GOM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BAUD:</hi> Yet foraſmuch as there are but few among us, to whom either the <hi>Book,</hi> or <hi>Author</hi> is known, I cannot but think it fit, that the reſt ſhould have ſome brief <hi>Account</hi> both of the <hi>One</hi> and of the <hi>Other;</hi> which when
<pb facs="tcp:49820:5"/>I have given, may (I hope) be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to beſpeak their attentive <hi>Peruſal</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> As to the <hi>BOOK;</hi> it treats of the moſt important and neceſſary (though withal the moſt neglected) <hi>Subject</hi> of any other, <hi>viz,</hi> TRUE RELIGION. And here, as on the one hand, you will find it repreſented to us in its Primitive <hi>Beauty,</hi> and (if I may ſo ſay) Genuine Complexion, that muſt needs render it amiable to ſincere <hi>Souls,</hi> and inflame them with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Affections towards it: So on the other hand, you will ſee delineated its <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Apoſtacſie,</hi> in the Deprava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of its <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Manners,</hi> wherewith it has been imbaſed, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated and diſguis'd, to that degree, that in many Places where it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fs'd, there is little elſe to be found re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, beſides the bare <hi>Name</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>The ſad Conſideration whereof may well draw tears from the Eyes, and
<pb facs="tcp:49820:5"/>Sighs from the Hearts of all good <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and make them take up the Lamentation of the <hi>Holy</hi> Prophet; <hi>How is the Gold become dim! How is the moſt ſine Gold chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged!</hi> and put th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m upon haſt'ning out of <hi>BABYLON, which is become the habitation of Devils, the hold of all foul Spirits, and the Cage of every unclean Bird.</hi> Well may it ſtir them up to call mightily upon God, <hi>and give him no reſt, till he eſtabliſh and make</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>a Praiſe in the whole Earth; till he build up again the Tabernacle of</hi> David <hi>that is fallen down, and bring forth thoſe Times of Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of the Reſtitution of all things, which he has ſpoken of by the Mouth of all his Holy Prophets ſince the World began.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor ſhould ſuch earneſt <hi>Prayers</hi> be unaccompanied with as earneſt <hi>Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours</hi> to make way for that deſirable
<pb facs="tcp:49820:6"/>
               <hi>Reformation</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new'd</hi> State of <hi>Religion,</hi> by doing our beſt (every one in his reſpective Station and Calling) for the Removal of thoſe Corruptions that ſo notoriouſly obſtruct it.</p>
            <p>Theſe appear to have been the main <hi>Ends</hi> of <hi>Monſieur de GOMBAUD</hi>'s expoſing here the miſchievous <hi>Abuſes</hi> and <hi>Errors</hi> long ſince crept-in among <hi>CHRISTIANS,</hi> and now ſo predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant (eſpecially) in the CHUCH of ROME, whoſe Falſe <hi>Worſhip</hi> and Bloody <hi>Tenets,</hi> with the <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> the <hi>Juggling</hi> and foul <hi>Practices</hi> of their <hi>Clergy,</hi> his <hi>DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COURSE</hi> ſeems to be chiefly le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd at.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> As to the <hi>AUTHOR's Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> and <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> I ſhall only ſay in ſhort, what is neceſſary for the <hi>REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER's</hi> Satisfaction, That he was a Perſon of great Virtue and Learning, born and bred in the <hi>Roman</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.
<pb facs="tcp:49820:6"/>But by Divine Illumination, aſſiſting his ſerious Study and impartial Examining of the Chief <hi>Points</hi> contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted between us, his Eyes were open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſee the groſs <hi>Errors</hi> of that <hi>Church,</hi> which he thereupon quitted, and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the REFORMATION; perſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein conſtant to the end, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the many <hi>Temptations</hi> he met with to draw him back, for above half an Age together; during which time he liv'd in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> under the Reigns of no leſs than <hi>three</hi> ſeveral Kings, viz. <hi>Henry IV, Lewis XIII,</hi> and <hi>Lewis XIV;</hi> and was there (if not by all, at leaſt by the <hi>Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi>) highly reſpected and eſteem'd for his great <hi>Genius,</hi> and other rare En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments of his <hi>Mind:</hi> Of which he has in <hi>this Treatiſe</hi> (among other his choice <hi>Works</hi>) given ſuch an <hi>Inſtance,</hi> as beſpeak him to be a very extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Perſon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49820:7"/>
            <p>Now, ſince <hi>Originals</hi> (eſpecially Ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellent ones) are accounted generally to loſe ſomewhat of Spirit by <hi>Tranſlations;</hi> I hope allowance may be granted to this of mine, if it come not up to the Grace and Force of <hi>Monſieur de GOMBAUD</hi>'s Expreſſion; who has a <hi>Style</hi> peculiar to himſelf, not eaſie for any to imitate. But ſetting this aſide, I may preſume to ſay, I have render'd him faithfully; ſo that, whoever ſhall take the pains to read this Tranſlation, may enjoy the whole <hi>Senſe</hi> of the <hi>AUTHOR,</hi> though, perhaps, in a leſs taking and Ornamental <hi>Dreſs.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſuch as it is, I doubt not but the CHRISTIAN READER will meet with <hi>THAT</hi> in it, will abundantly rccom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence him for the time he ſhall ſpend in the peruſing of it; by filling his Heart with a lively Senſe of the tranſcendent Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of our Moſt HOLY RELIGION, which <hi>Monſieur de GOMBAUD</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to have been ſo ſtrongly affected and inflamed with, in the Writing of this <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</hi> But I ſtop here; as being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to keep the READER any longer from that Edifying <hi>Entertainment</hi> here prepared for him.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>FAREWEL.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49820:7"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE OF THE Chriſtian Religion.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p n="1">I. SINCE I have begun to make uſe of my Reaſon and Underſtanding, I have a thouſand times reflected upon the Beauty of this Univerſe, the Order of its Parts, the mutual Services they lend one another, and the Eternal Laws they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49820:8"/>obſerve. A thouſand times, I ſay, have I conſider'd all theſe Wonders, and the cuſtom of ſeeing them has not leſſen'd my admiration of them. I have taken notice that all this great <hi>World</hi> is nothing elſe but a <hi>Viſible Word,</hi> that proves a GOD ſo evidently, that in compariſon of it all our Eloquence and Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick is dumb, or at beſt ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and inconſiſtent with it ſelf, that the more it endeavours on this account, the more it ſeems to hide what it would demonſtrate. I have ſeen that all things in Nature conſtantly perform their reſpective Functions, and anſwer the end and perfection of their Creation, MAN only excepted, who has from the beginning taken part with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils and Enemies of GOD, by offending him with ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, who had beſtow'd ſo many Favours upon him, and made
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49820:8"/>him ſuch as it was poſſible for him to be, without being God, but an Image of Him. As the firſt conception of his Mind was a Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Pride and Vain-glory, ſo the firſt Production of his Body was a <hi>Cain,</hi> a Murtherer of his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and all the Children he has brought into the World have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited his Raſhneſs, and Rebellion; and conſequently his Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Puniſhment. I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered Men in general, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that ſome of them were of the Nature of Devils, others of Beaſts, and many of both together: that their hands were full of Blood, Extortions, Violence, and Rapine; In ſhort, that their whole Exerciſe was nothing elſe but a kind of Monopoly and Robbery.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Then was I ſeized with a ſecret horror and grief, which like a ſhadow of Death, brought a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49820:9"/>Cloud upon the faireſt days of my Life. Nothing could comfort me, neither the conſideration that God had made me a Man, nor that I was one of thoſe that bear the Name of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſeeing they were at variance together, and that Ignorance and Malice were as common amongſt them, as with <hi>Barbarians</hi> and <hi>Infidels.</hi> Nothing was more contrary to me, than thoſe I thought like my ſelf, and I was reduced to this neceſſity, either to make my ſelf odious to all by an Everlaſting Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or to follow their Examples; and thereby be in ſome ſort, an Accomplice with them in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and unfaithfulneſs. In the mean time I obſerve that the ſame accidents equally ſurpriz'd both Old and Young, and I could not perſwade my ſelf, that Rational Beings could feel any true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49820:9"/>in ſo great an Uncertainty of what muſt happen to them. My Reaſon it ſelf, and all the Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions it enabled me to make, did but ſerve to increaſe my ſorrow, till I carefully and ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the <hi>Divine Oracles</hi> of the moſt ancient Writings, which aſſured me, that God had reſerved ſome to himſelf who bore <hi>a Mark in their Foreheads;</hi> which the Angels re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and whom the Deſtroyer doth not approach in the Day of Vengeance; That this World was nothing elſe but a Place of Tryal to diſcern the <hi>Good</hi> from the <hi>Bad,</hi> and a <hi>Way</hi> by which we are to paſs through <hi>Darkneſs</hi> to <hi>Light,</hi> and from <hi>Miſery</hi> to <hi>Felicity:</hi> Words I ſhould have heard with more fear than aſſurance, ſeeing there were ſo few that could or would mind them; if they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves had not taught me, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49820:10"/>
                  <hi>Shepheards</hi> and <hi>Fiſhermen</hi> do much better underſtand them, than the <hi>Diſputers of this World,</hi> and <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers;</hi> and that for the true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending of them, there is not ſo much need of <hi>Logick,</hi> as of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Piety.</hi> That they teach a Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that does not puff Men up, but makes them humble, and yet gives the moſt Humble and Lowly courage enough to profeſs it open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before the Proudeſt and Greateſt Men in the World, and every day to venture their own Lives in the attempt of ſaving of others from Death.</p>
               <p n="3">III. All theſe Divine Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, being accompanied with a Spirit of Comfort have calmed my Soul, and I have found my ſelf, as it were, renew'd and transformed on a ſudden, in ſuch a manner, that though my former grief has not quite left me, at leaſt its nature is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49820:10"/>changed, and has now no other cauſe but my Sins and Infirmities. And if ſtill I entertain any fears, they are ſuch as ſerve only to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure me the more, and make me preſs with greater eagerneſs <hi>towards the Mark,</hi> which <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> have ſet before me. In this I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, not as for ſome tranſitory Oblectation, which nothing can ſatisfie, and which at its full finds a want of many things; but as for an all-ſufficient and perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Good, which increaſeth by Communication, and which I may be very liberal of without the leaſt diminiſhing of it. This is that makes me now freely offer what I have received, and to joyn my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires with thoſe of ſuch Faithful Souls as Providence has ſown and mix'd with others, to the end that the Voice of Truth may be heard every where, and leave them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49820:11"/>out excuſe, who having heard ſhall not believe, or who being Traitors to themſelves for ſome Worldly Conſiderations ſhall fear to know it, leſt thereby they ſhould be obliged to follow it. The Days are coming when thoſe very Men will perhaps accuſe us for our not having ſaid enough to them, and for our Cowardiſe in not reproving of them, and will endeavour to charge their wilful Ignorance and hardneſs of Heart upon our weakneſs or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. And yet, we no ſooner open our Mouths that way, but ſome ſay they pity us, or will laugh at and deſpiſe us, and the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable uſage we receive from them, is to be looked upon as ſilly and extravagant Fellows. Others grow angry with us, and are ready to tear us in pieces, revile us and take us for <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers,</hi> though our Crime be of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49820:11"/>ſuch a nature as that we deſire no better than to have our Judges fully informed of it, and own it before all the World.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. But to whom ſhall we ſpeak? <hi>Idolaters</hi> will never underſtand us. All the <hi>Prophets</hi> have denounced a Curſe againſt them, which takes away their Underſtanding, and makes them like that they Worſhip. Neither will we be underſtood by weak Minds, and deſtitute of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for ſuch cannot apprehend any thing, being more apt to be troubled, than inſtructed; and if they be Wicked, they are offended to hear Words, that Condemn them. And theſe are by ſo much the more dangerous, as they are more Witty and Learned; They do nothing but uſe tricks, and wreſt both Words and Senſe. The cleareſt Propoſitions when they pleaſe become dark and doubtful;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49820:12"/>they can prove and deny every thing alike, and by a juſt Judgment for their not being willing to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Truth they are grown ſuch miſerable wretches, as not to be able to underſtand them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; they are ſo given up to the ſtudy of things ſuperfluous, that they have loſt the Care of thoſe that are neceſſary; an Humane Science which they have made the Judge of that which is Divine, hath render'd them worſe, than if they were altogether ignorant. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, as Men will not be eaſily perſwaded of that which they don't like, ſo methinks I hear the Wiſe Men and Courtiers of this Age cry, <hi>Pray tell us things pleaſing to us, and be not wiſer than the Church.</hi> They will be no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than their Fathers, nor follow other Cuſtoms, than thoſe of their Town and Country; the Eſtates
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49820:12"/>they there poſſeſs, or rather, which poſſeſs them, not permitting them ſo much as to think of applying themſelves to a Profeſſion, that might in the leaſt be prejudicial to them; and they will have God and Religion to buckle to their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, let it coſt what it will. <hi>How is it poſſible</hi> (ſay they) <hi>not to live after the way and mode of the World, or to have different Opinions from theirs that are in poſſeſſion of Chairs and Pulpits, and of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in vogue, to oppoſe the Belief of People, Magiſtrates, and Princes, and to expoſe ones ſelf to the Cenſure and Contradiction of all?</hi> Thus to ſpeak of Reformation, is to be a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Fellow, a Fanatick, and what not: Yea Licentiouſneſs is grown to that degree, that it cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide good and wholeſom Remedies. Piety is almoſt wholly turn'd to Superſtition; and look which way
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49820:13"/>you will, you'll find that Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo great, that there is need not only of a <hi>Flood</hi> to waſh the Earth, but of a Univerſal <hi>Confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration</hi> to conſume it.</p>
               <p n="5">V. To what purpoſe then is ſo much talk? And what Illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or new face ſhall we give to ſo many old Inſtructions, which are always new, becauſe always ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary? If a <hi>Summary</hi> of ſome few <hi>Articles,</hi> a ſhort <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> ſhould not be thought ſufficient to make the beſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> in the World, yet is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of Man's Duty omitted in either <hi>Teſtament?</hi> Nevertheleſs, ſince he that puts his <hi>Word</hi> into our <hi>Hearts,</hi> will have it alſo in our <hi>Mouths,</hi> to the end, that <hi>being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted we may alſo labour for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of our Brethren,</hi> let us not hold our peace when there is ſo great need of our ſpeaking, or at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49820:13"/>leaſt, let us (if poſſible) write ſuch things as Men may not ſcorn to read. But take we great heed of imitating thoſe Ambitious Writers who ſeek for Reputation from the Number or Bulk of their Volumes, wherewith they over-load Men's minds, not conſidering that this multiplicity of Words intimates no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than the difficulty they have to apprehend rightly, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacity to expreſs fully what they would ſay. Let us ſpeak therefore in ſpite of all oppoſition and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying, <hi>to try whether we can ſave ſome by fear, plucking them, as it were, out of the Fire,</hi> Jude 23. and ſee whether God will not open the heart of ſome <hi>Naaman</hi> among Men, 2 <hi>Kings,</hi> 5.15. and of ſome <hi>Lydia</hi> among Women, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:49820:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p n="6">VI. I Have conſider'd that thoſe Holy Men, who were the firſt Pen-men of Holy Writ, and taught us the Laws of Living well, and the Way to Salvation, did not trouble themſelves to find out Arguments, or give any expreſs Demonſtration in proof of a Deity; as not imagining we could be Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Creatures, and doubt of ſo evident a Truth. Indeed we muſt confeſs that every thing does in its own Language ſo loudly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim the ſame, that this vaſt U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe ſeem to be nothing elſe but a great Body, which God is pleaſed to make uſe of to render himſelf viſible, who of his own Nature is Inviſible. Beſides, the Natural Notions we have of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Principles that make us diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49820:14"/>between Good and Evil; the Terrors of Conſcience, thoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of Reaſon, that carry us ſo far above our own ſelves, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſearch after a ſupreme Good, and the deſire of Perfection and Immortality, render him much more ſenſible to our Mind, than he is to our Eyes. Therefore, whether we enter into our ſelves, or look abroad, we meet with him every where, and the ſenſe of him is ſo Univerſal, that it muſt needs proceed from Nature, and they who have it not, proclaim them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Monſters and Unnatural. For a Man to deny a God and his Providence (ſay the Wiſe and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious) is to be Deaf to his own Voice, and as it were, a Stranger to himſelf.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Nevertheleſs, ſome Men there are in the World who enjoy the ſweetneſs of Light and Life,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49820:15"/>and yet for all that do not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Author of them, or if they do ſo in appearance, 'tis only to avoid the Name of <hi>Atheiſts.</hi> Men that accommodate themſelves to all manner of Religions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have none, and can ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther drop or careſs them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they may be ſerviceable or prejudicial to their Worldly Intereſts and Pleaſures. They will allow no Laws but what their Luſts preſcribe, and the Juſteſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſeem the moſt Cruel to them; the Name of a Deity either offends them, or moves them not at all. They, as far as in them lies, would deſtroy him, who gave them their Being, and ſooth themſelves into an unbelief of That, which if they believed they would be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged both to reverence and fear. Their Libertine humour never gives leave to inform themſelves;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49820:15"/>and certainly they never read at all, or if they do, it is without Meditation; and if they Meditate, being naturally Wicked, they turn every thing to their own nature; and yet forſooth they muſt paſs for Wits and Men of Parts, and think themſelves, Head and Shoulders, above others, when from ſome infamous Sophiſter they have pick'd up two or three falſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for their deteſtable Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they inſolently extol before the Ignorant, or in the Company of Profane Wretches like themſelves. But theſe ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, they are fain to be ſilent; or if they ſpeak, it is only to ſhew themſelves meer <hi>Ignorants,</hi> in that they are always asking Queſtions without anſwering any. And it grieves me to ſay, that many Princes and Great Men are ſo far from deteſting theſe Monſters,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49820:16"/>that they often find them better Company than other Men, and admit them into their Familiarity and Confidence; not conſidering, that by this means they become their Accomplices, and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves guilty of High-Treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Divine Majeſty. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe, forſooth, Converſations and Entertainments are dull and inſipid; Here it is they are highly countenanced and reſpected; here they are pamper'd with Dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and where they are moſt bound to be thankful, there it is they belch forth the blackeſt Blaſphemies. Their Sayings are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived here with the greateſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe and appear ſo much the more witty, by how much the more bold they are, and attack God himſelf? Men truly the moſt ingrateful and the leaſt reaſonable of any other in the World, who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49820:16"/>are ready to thank themſelves for all the good things they receive, ſeeing they acknowledge no other Cauſe thereof but their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry or good Fortune. The very Sons of the <hi>Devil</hi> (whoſe Name imply's a <hi>Slanderer</hi>) that would fain Signalize themſelves by attempting the ſame thing with their Father, who did ever make it his endeavour to oppoſe the Truth.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. But ſince they will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge no Wit paramount to their own; perhaps 'tis by their Care and Power, that the <hi>Earth</hi> is counterpois'd by its own <hi>Weight,</hi> and ſurrounded with ſo vaſt an <hi>Ocean</hi> without being drown'd in it. Belike, 'tis by their Induſtry and Providence, that ſo ſolid an <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is pierced in ſo many places by ſuch a vaſt number of <hi>Canals,</hi> ſpringing with Waters, that quench
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49820:17"/>the thirſt of all Living Creatures, and conſtitute Rivers ſo abounding with Fiſh, ſo Fertile and Condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive to Commerce through the whole World. 'Tis by their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, no doubt, that the <hi>Sun</hi> riſes at the ſet time to enlighten them, when they are ſatisfied with Sleep; and that the <hi>Seaſons</hi> return to fill their Senſes with all variety of Pleaſures. Now, if in this they can't but own their Weakneſs, what folly is it in them not to grant that there are Intellects more powerful and ſublime than theirs, employ'd in theſe wonderful Operations; and that we muſt at laſt come up to and ſtop, at ſome one that is Superiour to all others, which being finite have a Beginning, and conſequently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon That which has none, and is Infinite? For otherwiſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the ſmalleſt to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49820:17"/>greateſt, Men would endleſly paſs from one Cauſe to another, and never find the Firſt and Laſt, which alone deſerves the Name of DEITY. O ſhame of Men, that now a-days we muſt be at the pains to prove a GOD! What greater affront can be put upon our Kind than to ſhew them that which is continually preſent to all their Senſes? Is not this to go about to teach the Art of Seeing, to them whoſe Eyes are open, and that of Reaſon to ſuch as profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Men? Or ſhall we need to add to theſe Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons their continual Repetitions, who have undertaken ſo high, but withal ſo reaſonable a Defence? Indeed, if God were not, how could the World exiſt? Or muſt it be its own Workman and Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, or have had a being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was? How could both
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49820:18"/>theſe ſtand, and yet be but one and the ſame World? Or, if it were Eternal, and Independent upon any Superiour Cauſe, that admirable Oeconomy, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not proceed but from an infinite Intellect, and thoſe ſtupendous Virtues which it ſeverally Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates to all its Parts, would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſort, prove (what many have fancied) it to be a God. For what the leaſt appearance is there, that its Beauty, Order, and Duration ſhould be the effect of blind and heedleſs Chance, or that we owe to her Conduct, Prudence, and Power, ſo ſteady and well regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated a Succeſſion of Times and Motions, and that ſuch is her Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Might, as to make Cauſes ſo remote one from another, to co-operate one and the ſelf-ſame end? After all their pains, this would be ſtill a God, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49820:18"/>another Name, and theſe Monſtrous Blaſphemers would ſtill find in every place what their guilty Souls deſire to meet no where. For, what is Fortune or Chance? but an empty Name, a Vain Idol that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts only in our imagination, and to which we through Error attribute all Events, and the Effects of all Cauſes unknown to us, to whom it appears greater or leſſer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as we have more or leſs knowledge; and if we could ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Ignorance out of the World, Fortune would be fain to pack with her. This therefore is the Deity of the Ignorant, to whom the Wiſe pay no Vows, nor make Offerings; and I am aſtoniſh'd how they can think they have any reaſon, that ſpeak for it, ſince (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Scheme) they muſt believe that it is to Chance they owe their Being, and conſequently
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49820:19"/>can neither move, act, nor ſpeak, but by Chance. Others there are who would ſeem to believe a God, but are ſo ſolicitous and concern'd for his repoſe, as to take from him the Care, if not of the whole <hi>World,</hi> at leaſt of all <hi>Sublunary Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings;</hi> fancying this would be too much trouble for him, as if he ſtood in need of their Impious folly to eaſe him. Is not this to deny him, whilſt they pretend to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him, and raſhly confine the Actions of a Power that in its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is infinite? Is not this to frame to ones ſelf a God, that does not ſo much as perform the part of a Man, and to attribute to him an Underſtanding depriv'd of Council, a Will without Effect, and a Bounty without Communicativeneſs; and to ſay all in one Word, a Being without being, and leſs than that of the Elements, which is next to Non-Entity.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49820:19"/>
               <p n="9">IX. For, not to inſiſt any more upon that Univerſal Relation, and Concatenation of Cauſes and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which plainly demonſtrate that things Superiour ſtand in need of the help of thoſe that are Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, and that it neceſſarily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the ſame Wiſdom and Power both to make them and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them; Let theſe Gigantick Wits ſtand forth and tell me, Who is it that chaſtiſes <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>People</hi> in his wrath, that removes <hi>Scepters</hi> from one Hand into another, that changes, as it were in an inſtant, the Face of <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Empires,</hi> and that (to ſhew it is HE that does it) fails not of denouncing it a long time before by the Mouth of his Meſſengers, Prophets and Miniſters? Who was it that did once puniſh the Sins of Men with ſo dreadful a Deluge own'd by all Nations; and by whoſe Advice
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49820:20"/>was it that one ſingle Family was then ſav'd? Who is it that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed the like Flood ſhould never happen any more, and has ſo well kept his Promiſe? What Intellect did foreſee three or four thouſand Years before the Event, the Coming of the MESSIAS, of whom alſo Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets did ſpeak in ſuch a manner, as one would think they had no leſs ſeen him than the Apoſtles? From whom but God himſelf, or ſome Angel ſent by him, could proceed thoſe Predictions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Poſterity of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> and the <hi>Lamp,</hi> that was to be preſerved for him in his Family; the diſperſed and rejected <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Converted Nations? If they tell me there are Mathematicians, Aſtrologers, and Magicians, that can predict future Events, I will ſtill ask them, what Hand did write them in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49820:20"/>in ſuch fair Characters as Men might read them? And who has put the ſigns of theſe things in the Stars, or rather the Virtues and Cauſes which the ſame Men cannot comprehend? They that are not touched with theſe Conſiderations muſt needs be ſtrangely poſſeſs'd with a blind Paſſion that diverts their Reaſon to ſomewhat elſe, and makes them paſs from <hi>Cuſtom</hi> to <hi>Hardneſs,</hi> and from <hi>Ignorance</hi> to <hi>Security.</hi> And yet we ſee theſe Men very Wiſe and Prudent in Worldly Concerns; Their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Stupidity ſeem only to be about Divine Matters. And I am much miſtaken if moſt of them do not carry their Accuſers and Judge in their own Boſom, who ſooner or later will force them to cry out, as well as many others, <hi>We have wearied our ſelves in the ways of Iniquity, and are conſumed in our own Wickedneſs.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49820:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p n="10">X. THus, all that we ſee, ſpeaks to us of God, and convinces us of his Exiſtence. But what he is, no Objects nor any Diſcourſe of ours can ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent. Yet what we know of him is ſufficient to make us believe and adore thoſe his Perfections we know not. Whether therefore the Progreſs of Cauſes and Effects be not infinite, and all things arrive or tend viſibly to their End; Whether from the Old Book, in compariſon of which all others are New, we learn the Origine of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Nations; Whether the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of Heaven grow weak, and both the Age and Strength of Man decreaſe in compariſon of what Sacred and Profane Hiſtories tell us was heretofore; it does evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49820:21"/>appear that God has crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the World, and for the Top-Stone of ſo many Maſter-pieces, he has made Man after his own Image, that is to ſay, wholly conformable that is to ſay, wholly conformable to his Will; not by a Conformity of Eſſence, but of Imitation, and perfect with that degree of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which the moſt Noble Creature was capable of, and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for his Felicity. He held a moſt Honourable Rank between A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimals and Angels; He was, as it were, the Tye and Band of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe, and the Center and End of all Created Beings, over which he would have born an Eternal Sway and Command, had he but once obey'd his Creator.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. But being not contented with the Favours and Munificence beſtow'd on him, he raſhly aſpircs to a Dignity above the Supreme, and deſirous to mount higher than
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49820:22"/>the very Top, and to ſeek (as it were) ſomething beyond Exiſtence he fell down to the loweſt Pit, and wanted but little of returning to that Nothing out of which he was made. What a preſumption and raſhneſs for Man to ſtrive to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to God! What incredulity to accuſe him of a Lie or of Envy! What ingratitude and rebellion to ſubſtitute the Devil in his Place! What lack of Charity, or what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Neglect towards his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to ſell them before they were Born, and put them into Slavery before they knew what Liberty was! He little imagin'd he ſhould be thought the worſt Father in the World, and that the Curſe he had drawn upon himſelf ſhould reach from one end of the Earth to the other, and from the Beginning to the determination of all Ages, and be the moſt certain Inheritance he
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49820:22"/>ſhould leave to his Poſterity. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did he foreſee that inſtead of that Correſpondence or Society he had with the Angels, and his Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God himſelf, his Unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Succeſſors ſhould only converſe with Devils, under whoſe Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny they would groan continually; and that to live among Men would be to walk among Lions and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, or among Vipers and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons: Nor that inſtead of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Spring, which he had begun to enjoy, and might have tranſmitted to them, they ſhould undergo the rigour of a hard Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or be conſumed by the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burning and Scorching heat of Summer; and that inſtead of thoſe fine Trees he beheld in the Earthly Paradiſe, and of the ſweet Flowers and Fruits he could gather there, they ſhould frequently ſee nothing elſe but Gallows and Racks, Graves
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49820:23"/>and Dead-Men's Bones. He did not foreſee that beſides the ſweat of Labour, the miſery of Want, the pain of Diſeaſes, and the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Death, there would be Judgments that ſhould overthrow Towns and Cities, and lay waſte whole Provinces; That ſometimes Mortality would be ſo great, and the Dead themſelves ſo dreadful, that there ſhould be none to be found either to Mourn for, or Bury them; and that at other times Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would be ſo deprav'd, as that Men would devour one another, and Children being all torn to bits and pieces ſhould return into their own Mothers Wombs. In ſhort, he did not foreſee, that moſt of his Progeny would be ſo abominably Wicked as to perſecute the moſt Innocent and Righteous of their Brethren rather than imitate them; That they would not content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49820:23"/>ſelves only to ſtone ſome, and murther others; but would be ſo induſtrious as to find out Torments whereby to oblige them to renounce the Truth, and worſhip Wood and Stone, or elſe undergo all the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el and Barbarous Uſage that the Malice of Hell can invent. No, he did not foreſee all this; and the Devil who made him believe he ſhould have his Eyes open'd, aim'd at nothing elſe than quite ſhutting of them, that ſo he might precipitate him into an Abyſs; whence it was not ro be thought there ſhould ever be any Power of Man or Angel capable to retrieve him.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. How has this Fall diſfigur'd him, and what proportion or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance is there of what he now is to what he was before! He is aſhamed of himſelf, and has no ſight but of his Nakedneſs, nor
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49820:24"/>knowledge but of his Error. From the Image of God which he was, he is transformed, as it were in an inſtant, into that of the Devil; and there remains nothing in him of his priſtine Innocence, but the grief of having loſt it. Who ſhall comfort him for this Loſs, and what can he expect from his Reaſon that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerved to betray and undo him? How is it poſſible that he who could not keep up while he ſtood, ſhould get up again when fallen? What can he hope for either from the Angels, or God himſelf; having broken that Law whereby he was oblig'd to Obedience, or to Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Puniſhment that is of the ſame age with the Offence, troubles and afflicts him already without inter miſſion, and he has no more Life left him, but to feel the continual ſtrokes and attacks of Death. And which is worſe, ſtill the offence is heightned
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49820:24"/>proportionably to the Dignity of the Perſon offended. So that as he has ſinned againſt him that is Infinite, ſo muſt he dye, or ſuffer infinitely. O what confuſion of thoughts! What remorſe and what fears diſturb his Mind, eſpecially conſidering that he had no leſs been informed of his Duty, than threatned with his Diſgrace; and the more to quicken in him the care of his own Preſervation, it ſeems the Sentence of Death ſhould in ſome ſort, as one would think, have prevented his Crime? To what deſpair is he reduc'd, and what can he think in this Miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble State? Save only this, that God never makes a thing, which he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards repents to have made; that he does not build up to pull down, and that the Glory of ſuch a Workman will not ſuffer his Work to periſh. That it was not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49820:25"/>likely that the moſt Excellent of all Creatures ſhould be appointed to Eternal Woes, and that being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, and the fault not wholly his own, he ſhould be obliged to make the ſame Satisfaction with the Devils, which continues ſtill, and ſhall never end.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. Howbeit, he diſcover'd no Expedient for his Deliverance, and could not imagine there were any means capable of procuring him GOD's <hi>Mercy,</hi> without doing Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence to his <hi>Juſtice.</hi> This is what neither he, nor we his Poſterity, could ever have conceiv'd: And thereupon ſome lull'd themſelves aſleep and became Atheiſts; others framed Gods to themſelves after their own way, and fell to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. This unhappy Inclination (yet ſo natural and ſo ſtrong that 'tis grown almoſt to an univerſal Fury) did ſo pervert their Senſes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49820:25"/>and Underſtanding, that they would have the Objects of their Worſhips to be as themſelves, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal and Viſible, and not being able to imagine any thing beyond themſelves, they attributed Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Paſſions to them, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Services for them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Vanity of their own thoughts. They not only degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded themſelves beneath the nature of Man, when they paid Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their own kind, but made themſelves leſs than Beaſts, by Worſhipping them all. Nay, they adored the moſt Vile and Abject of all Creatures, that were ſo far from having any Ray or Mark of the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that many times they were ſuch as had not ſo much as any ſign of Life in them; Yea for fear leſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing Horrid and Execrable ſhould be wanting in their Idolatry, they worſhipped the very <hi>Infernal
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49820:26"/>Powers</hi> and Enemies of the <hi>Creator.</hi> Many judging well there muſt be a better ſtate for Man than that of this World, inſtead of enquiring whether there was not ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Word that could inform them of their chief End and ſupreme Good, conſulted only ambiguous and Deviliſh Oracles. Inſtead of the only and true Remedy that was able to cleanſe them from all filthineſs of Sin, they ſought for nothing but Crooked and By-ways; and therein wearied themſelves with <hi>Ceremonies, Abſtinences, Purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, Faſts,</hi> and <hi>Offerings;</hi> all which had no other effect, than to add new afflictions to their Lives. For what <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> what <hi>Beaſts,</hi> what <hi>Hecatombs,</hi> could ever make atonement for the Tranſgreſſions of one ſingle Man? Or rather, what Man conceiv'd as he is in Sin, could ever ſatisfie, I don't ſay for
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49820:26"/>others, but even for his own ſelf? And what elſe could he offer in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering up of himſelf, but <hi>Ingratitude, Envy, Hatred, Malice, Thoughts</hi> of <hi>Vanity,</hi> and <hi>Words</hi> of <hi>Falſhood?</hi> Nay, what are his very <hi>Virtues</hi> but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis'd <hi>Vices?</hi> What is his <hi>Prudence</hi> but <hi>Deceit,</hi> his <hi>Valour</hi> but <hi>Raſhneſs,</hi> and his <hi>Wiſdom</hi> but <hi>Hypocriſie?</hi> If he prays, he does it but perfuncto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, and out of Cuſtom; and if at any time he ſhews ſome Zeal, 'tis not ſo much his Love to God that excites and inflames him, as his apprehenſion of ſome Evil that he is threatned with, or the ſenſe of that which preſſes him. What can he do better than to make a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Confeſſion of his Sins, for which, if he be judged according to his Demerits, he ought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect nothing elſe but the Sentence of Death and Eternal Damnation? Therefore if all Humane Reaſon
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49820:27"/>was never able to find out the means of Sanctifying ſo much as one ſingle Man; nor all Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy to make one Believer, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover a Good not to be ſnatch'd away by Death; What remains but that we ſhould believe what the beſt inſpired Men could beſt tell us, <hi>viz.</hi> That we muſt have recourſe to the firſt Beginning; That the means was to be Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, and that none but God could reveal it?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p n="14">XIV. 'TIS a thing moſt certain, That as Man was not made by Chance; ſo neither was he created in vain; That his End can never be either to ſuffer Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Torments, or to return to that Nothing out of which he was taken,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49820:27"/>and that the ſame Power that gave him Being, muſt ſave him. Should not he, who by the ſingle Sparks of that Divine Image remaining in him, is able to meaſure the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens without leaving the Earth, think we be Immortal? What would elſe become of ſo many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations and Promiſes, or who is it that hath taken ſo much care to deceive us? What would Juſtice and Piety be more than vain emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Names, to cheat the World withal? And to what purpoſe ſo much Regard and Caution, if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Life there be nothing to be hoped for? No doubt, our Natural Remiſneſs and Senſuality would not be wanting in adviſing us to follow the beaten Road, to enjoy the things Preſent, without troubling our head with the Future, and to live like Beaſts, ſince we muſt die like them? But away
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49820:28"/>with all theſe profane and raſh Thoughts. The firſt Act of the Creator anſwers for all the reſt; and he that has made us of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, is as able to retrieve us from Death. Should he be contented to ſuffer his own Image to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd and defam'd? Should the Devil be Conqueror in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, and raiſe his Trophies over the Works of the Almighty? No certainly; the firſt State of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence was not the End of Man: How good ſoever he might be then, he was to be ſtill better, and his latter end more Bleſſed than his Beginning. But it was requiſite he ſhould be expoſed to his own deſires, and <hi>left to the Counſel of his own hand,</hi> as well for his Tryal, as to the end he might know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that this knowledge might be as a Step to him to raiſe him up to that of his Creator. Perhaps he
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49820:28"/>would have thought he was capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of maintaining himſelf without the Help of any other Power; not reflecting that there is but one pure Holy and true Being, on whom all others do depend, and without whom either we muſt not be at all, or be Eternally Miſerable.</p>
               <p n="15">XV. To the end therefore that all Men might know they are not to rely upon the ſtrength and virtue vouchſafed them, God has given them the means to try themſelves, and acknowledge that they are all of them equally fallen by the fall of One; that they are naturally the Slaves of Sin, and conſequently Tributaries to Hell and Death. He gave them his Law, which how perfect ſoever it be, yet brings nothing to its full Perfection; whoſe Juſtice ſerves on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make them the more guilty, whoſe Inſtructions are but in order
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49820:29"/>to confound them, and which ſeems not to promiſe them good things, but to make them deſpair of ever attaining them It is a Letter that kills, an intolerable Yoke, a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of Death, which is ſo far from juſtifying Men, that it ranks them all under one and the ſame Condemnation. Or to ſpeak more favourably of it; It is a Glaſs wherein they may ſee what they were, what they are, and what they ſhall be; It is a Flower, whoſe Fruit is the greateſt Favour that can ever happen to them; It is a Candle that lightens them du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Night, till the Sun riſe upon them.</p>
               <p n="16">XVI. Now, as the incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Unity, which comprehends all multiplicity, is the ſupreme Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of God, ſo in like manner Union with God is the ſupreme Perfection of Man. But we are
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49820:29"/>not able to raiſe up our ſelves to him, unleſs he firſt draws us, or rather vouchſafes to come down to us. This is the Myſtery of our Redemption, which even they themſelves who had received the Promiſes of it, confirmed by ſo many Signs and Miracles, did ſee ſo far off, and through ſo many ſhadows and ſo much darkneſs, that they were better able to believe and hope for it, than comprehend it. Seeing the vaſt diſtance there is between Heaven and Earth, they could not think of any means to fill up their great Abyſs, and were not informed there were any Steps by which they might aſcend to Heaven, ſave only by <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Yet Reaſon does for all that give its aſſent to things that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen beyond Reaſon it ſelf; and helps us apprehend that at laſt, which at firſt it could not ſo much
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49820:30"/>as in the leaſt make us imagine. Since therefore it teaches us that a Mean ought equally to partake of both Extremes, and doth unite them, howſoever diſagreeing they may be; that a Mediator ought to be capable of the Sentiments and Affections of both Parties he intends to reconcile, and ſet a juſt Eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate upon the Right or Wrong of either of them: Who doubts but that he that for this end is ſent to us from Heaven is fully poſſeſs'd of all the Qualities requiſite for him as ſuch; that he partakes of the Humane and Divine Nature; in a Word, that he is Man and God both together? Moreover, who doubts but that he is a Man conceiv'd otherwiſe than other Men, leſt his Natural Corruption and Sin ſhould make him incapable of an intimate eſſential Union with the Divine Juſtice and Purity? For
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49820:30"/>if he were not Man, we could have no ſhare in him, neither could his ſatisfaction be imputed to us. If he were not God, he could not communicate his Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Virtues, Glory and Felicity to us. If he were Man only, he could not overcome Death, nor raiſe himſelf from the Grave, but ſink under the Burthen, and be ſoon reduc'd to nothing: And if he were God only, he could not have Died, nor received from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that Payment to which we are bound by the Law. Therefore he muſt ſuffer, and yet be altogether incapable of Dying; he muſt die, and yet withal be Immortal too; He muſt deſcend into Hell, and come up thence again; He muſt be above all the Infernal Powers, and ſhew that to him truly belong all the ways that lead to, as well as the Iſſues from, Death. He that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49820:31"/>will deliver others from the Curſe, muſt undergo and overcome it; and to the end there might be ſome proportion between the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and the Puniſhment, there muſt be a Perſon of an infinite Worth and Excellency, to make a temporal and finite torment of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Merit. For certainly it is more with God that his Son dies for the Sins of the World, then to ſee all Mankind periſh together. Now, tho' there be no Law that allows the Innocent to ſuffer for the Guilty; neither is there any that forbids it, provided he offer himſelf willingly, and be not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely deſtroy'd by the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but have power as to lay down his Life ſo to take it up again.</p>
               <p n="17">XVII. O the Wonders of the Eternal Power and Wiſdom, who in the Beginning was pleaſed to take out of Man a Woman that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49820:31"/>cauſed us all to Die, that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards out of the Woman he might take a Man that will make us all alive again! Thus Humane, and Divine Nature in the fulneſs of time are by a ſtupendious Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry united together, and without any the leaſt alteration in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of either, the Son of God has joyn'd himſelf in Unity of Perſon with the Son of Man. I ſay the Son, and not the Father; for we cannot have him for an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſor, who is to be interceded with. He that does ſend cannot be ſent; and becauſe the Father does nothing by himſelf, but all things by his Son, it is reaſonable that he ſhould exert the Second Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who was the Author of the Firſt. And who could ſpeak bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on our behalf, than he who is the Word it ſelf? Who could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print the Divine Image better in us,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49820:32"/>than he that formed it there at firſt, or intitle us better to the right of Children, than he that poſſeſſes it in the higheſt degree? But it is not enough that he ſhould make ſatisfaction, and that this ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould be imputed to us, but he muſt alſo confer that Grace upon, and apply it to us; and this is the Office of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which equally proceeds from the <hi>Son</hi> and the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> He it is that enlightens and purifies us, that enables us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, love, and believe theſe Myſteries, that impregnates us, as he did the Bleſſed <hi>Virgin,</hi> and makes us conceive our <hi>Saviour.</hi> He is that Band of Love which unites us to the Divinity, that real Unction, wherewith we are all anointed, and thereby made Kings, Prophets and Prieſts. In ſhort, it is he that gives himſelf for a Pledge and Security of the Promiſes of the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49820:32"/>Life to come, of the Reſurrection, and Glory.</p>
               <p n="18">XVIII. This great Mediator therefore is come, ſuch as he was foretold, not like ſome great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, a <hi>Cyrus</hi> or an <hi>Alexander;</hi> but in the form of a Man full of ſorrows and acquainted with griefs, like one Conſecrated by ſuffering; to be a Propitiatory Victim for Mankind, whoſe Merit is ſufficient for all, but appliable only to them that believe in him. He is come not to ſhed another's Blood, but his own, and combate <hi>Rebellion</hi> with <hi>Obedience; Strength</hi> with <hi>Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; Pride</hi> with <hi>Humility;</hi> This is that which makes him appear grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more Divine; This is that which overcomes and raviſhes us into admiration, and obliges us to fall down and worſhip him. This is the ſole Object of Religion, which is not only the Art of ſaving
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49820:33"/>Man, but of making a <hi>God</hi> of him, without any the leaſt prejudice to the Divine <hi>Unity,</hi> or the Holy <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> For what name can be given to the Son of Man, who makes but one and the ſame Perſon with the Son of God? And of what Extract muſt we eſteem them to be, whom he has vouchſafed ſo far to honour, as to call them his Brethren? Now this RELIGION has been eſtabliſhed not by any <hi>Bribings, Companies,</hi> or <hi>Combinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> not by the <hi>Favour</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> or the <hi>Votes</hi> of <hi>People;</hi> not by the <hi>Subtilty</hi> of <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> or the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion</hi> of <hi>Orators;</hi> In a word, not by a Multitude of <hi>Men,</hi> as the <hi>Mahometan,</hi> nor a great Number of <hi>Gods,</hi> as the <hi>Pagan;</hi> but only by the plain Propoſal of a ſimple and naked <hi>Truth.</hi> Which <hi>Truth</hi> has, notwithſtanding all manner of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and Gain-ſaying, made it
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49820:33"/>ſelf to be heard throughout the World; and at its appearance has ſeen all <hi>Errors</hi> confounded, all <hi>Sects</hi> diſſipated and vaniſhing all Falſe <hi>Oracles</hi> ſtruck Dumb, and all <hi>Idols</hi> and their <hi>Worſhippers</hi> fall down before it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p n="19">XIX. AFter all that this RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIGION lays before us of the only Way for Man to be ſav'd, what can all the Religions in the World beſides teach us? And what can <hi>Mahomet</hi> pretend to perſwade us, if the Name of a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> be ſo odious to him, and he ſo little agree with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who does ſo perfectly agree with all the <hi>Prophets?</hi> Is it not a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing, that ſo many Men ſhould be inſpired in ſo different
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49820:34"/>Places, and at ſo different times, to proclaim the Coming of a Man, who was to be rejected of his own, and receiv'd of all the Nations of the Earth? Certainly, after what the Scriptures tell us, and the Commands and Counſels they give us, there is no more room left for <hi>Curioſity,</hi> but for <hi>Submiſſion</hi> and <hi>Obedience.</hi> Let thoſe who make their own Gods appoint them what Services they pleaſe: it muſt not be ſo with him, who is not made by our Opinion, but we are all made by him: Whoſe Will cannot be manifeſted to us by Imaginations or Conjectures, but only by his own Word. This is the Light he hath given us to be our Guide, and wo to them that call that Light Darkneſs. So high and excellent is the knowledge it raiſes us to, that no man can ever be ſuppoſed to have invented it:
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49820:34"/>Beſides it is ſo conformable to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that 'tis impoſſible to conſider it, and not to approve it. In the firſt place it diſcovers Man to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and makes him ſenſible of his own Weakneſs and Miſery; but immediately comforts him again; ſhewing him his Diſtemper, only to diſpoſe him to be preſented with a Remedy for it. It contains <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> and <hi>Predictions,</hi> which after ſo many Ages have been confirmed by the Events, and tend to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end but the <hi>Salvation</hi> of the <hi>Creature,</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>CREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TOR.</hi> The Natural <hi>Simplicity</hi> and <hi>Plainneſs;</hi> the <hi>Scope, Style, Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Energy, Duration,</hi> and ſo many other <hi>Signs</hi> that ſhine in it, are ſo clear an <hi>Evidence</hi> of its being <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> that it manifeſtly appears, that 'tis GOD himſelf that ſpeaks, and conſequently it behoves <hi>Man</hi> to give attention and be ſiilent.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49820:35"/>What <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the greateſt and moſt flouriſhing Empires in the World, was ever confirmed by their own Friends, as this is by its Foes? What other Hiſtory beſides this, begins with the World, continues from Age to Age, ſpeaks of things to come, as if they were preſent, and ends with the World it ſelf? This is the <hi>Way</hi> to <hi>Salvation,</hi> the <hi>Gate</hi> of <hi>Heaven;</hi> and whoever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in any other way is a <hi>Thief</hi> and a <hi>Robber.</hi> This is the <hi>Model</hi> of <hi>Perfection,</hi> that ſhews us what Good or what Evil we are capable of, and teaches us to examine, know, and reform our ſelves. This is the true <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> wherein the <hi>Tree</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> is to be found, the <hi>Leaves</hi> whereof are for the <hi>Healing</hi> of the <hi>Nations.</hi> In a Word, theſe are the ALMIGHTY's <hi>Letters,</hi> which he writes as well to his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> as his <hi>Friends,</hi> and are neither
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49820:35"/>cloſed nor ſeal'd up to any of them, whom he has appointed <hi>Heirs</hi> of <hi>Eternal Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">XX. Whoſoever therefore does know, that there is a Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the Inſtruction and Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Man in the Service he ought to pay to his God, and the Reward he may expect for it, and he is not careful to look into it, whatever ſhew of Religion ſuch a one may make, he is a <hi>Liar,</hi> an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> and a <hi>Deceiver</hi> of his own ſelf; ſeeing it is written for the <hi>Common People,</hi> as well as for the <hi>Learned;</hi> for <hi>Women,</hi> as well as for <hi>Men;</hi> for <hi>Children,</hi> as well as for <hi>Parents.</hi> And it is a bad ſign for thoſe, who have once read it, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps out of Curioſity, not to be affected with the Love of it, and continually deſire to read it over and over again. Is this to deal honeſtly and faithfully; or rather,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49820:36"/>is it not a ſiding with Satan, and being as it were at his Wages, and taking his pay, to hinder the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Men, by forbidding the reading of it to ſo many People of good will, who thirſt after the WORD of ETERNAL LIFE? Let <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Hereticks</hi> hide their falſe <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Errors,</hi> as much as they pleaſe, the GOSPEL of CHRIST, which is the TRUTH it ſelf, muſt be Viſible and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable to all; it muſt ſhine as bright as the day, and this Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Light muſt be no more hid than the Corporeal. Perhaps ſome will ſay, <hi>We need not ſo much Reading, nor ſo much Study; has not the</hi> Church <hi>preſcribed whatſoever is neceſſary for us, and are not we under the Conduct of Men that cannot err?</hi> But to this I anſwer, that there can be no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Error than that which perſwades us we cannot err; and that this
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49820:36"/>is raſhly to aſſume to our ſelves a Divine Property incommunicable to any Man, beſides Prophets and Apoſtles; and that ſo far, as they are commiſſionated to be the Bearers of the Word they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, and the Preachers of what has really been reveal'd to them. But perhaps, the WORD of GOD is not to be underſtood without the help of <hi>Plato</hi> or <hi>Ariſtotle?</hi> But I anſwer, that the Wiſe of this World are ſo much the farther from this Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, becauſe their <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is <hi>Folly</hi> before GOD, and prompts them to gain-ſay the Holy Spirit with Obſtinacy and Violence, as two Contraries are wont to do. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, 'tis but a part, or half of the Rule, and therefore not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient perfectly to inſtruct us about our <hi>Salvation?</hi> But ſay I, there is no Man ſo ſimple, nor ſo dull, but this will enable him to conceive
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49820:37"/>more good things than the moſt Holy can practiſe, and there is no Saint but comes far ſhort of the Perfection it propoſes.</p>
               <p n="21">XXI. Methinks, I hear theſe wilfully ignorant Perſons complain of the Difficulty of a Science, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which they never made any more Enquiry, than if the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Salvation did not at all concern them; and through a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, or rather, Superſtitious Scruple profeſs that they are not worthy to read it. 'Tis true, you are unworthy of the Favour that God is willing to ſhew you; but being he is pleaſed to do it, pray, who would you have to receive it for you? You ſuſpect him, and ſuppoſe his Word to be dangerous and dreadful, and that it is ſpoken or inſpir'd to no other end, but to lay Snares for Men's minds, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and undo them. You know
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49820:37"/>(ſay you) your own Weakneſs and Inſufficiency; and that you would be apt to wreſt or miſtake the meaning of it. Say rather, you know your own Malice and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and that you would turn that into rank Poiſon, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do convert into Sweet Hony. You ſay that Sacred WORD is dark and obſcure, whoſe firſt Words made the <hi>Light,</hi> that Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>Lamp,</hi> which was given us to this very end, that it might enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten us. You hear not that Word which the very Rocks have heard, and which does not only raiſe the Dead, but <hi>calls thoſe things that are not as if they were;</hi> which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands things out of Nothing, and the Command is obey'd. Confeſs therefore that you are leſs ſenſible than Rocks, than the Dead, yea than Nothing it ſelf. This is the proper Effect, Counſel, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49820:38"/>of your Guides and Maſters, who at once made their own Precepts to be regarded, and the Scripture deſpiſed; whoſe Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity cannot ſerve their Ambition, and who not daring to accuſe it of Lies, have given it the bad Name, that it is dark and obſcure; and not being able openly to gain-ſay it, have put their own Senſe upon it. And though it be full of ſtrict Prohibitions of adding any thing to, or taking ought from it, yet have they not contented themſelves to lay heavy Burthens upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and load them with new Ceremonies and Ordinances, which make the State of the Goſpel more intolerable than that of the Law: But their inſolence and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs has carried them to that exceſs, as to cut off ſome Commandments from the Law it ſelf; though one would think the Reſpect due to the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49820:38"/>Hand of God that wrote it, ſhould have exempted it from ſuch a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge, and render'd it for ever inviolable. Theſe Men ſtudy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity only to oppoſe and baffle the Scripture; and ſome of them have run over their <hi>Courſe</hi> of <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> and are admmitted <hi>Doctors,</hi> without ever having read it. Before they read it, they learn the Senſe of the School, and underſtand it not but by the falſe Light of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice. After all this, 'tis very hard for them to admit another im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, than what they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in their Youth; And then (O Vanity, wherewith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Devil deludes Men!) thus to underſtand it, is to be thought Learned.</p>
               <p n="22">XXII. I Know there are Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Prophecies in it, which were not underſtood even by thoſe who delivered them, and that the Knowledge thereof was reſerved
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49820:39"/>for them that ſhould ſee their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents. Neither is there one Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage threatning Men with Eternal Death, who cannot fully explain the Revelation. A Man may work out his own Salvation with leſs Difficulty, than to underſtand throughly all the Viſions of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi> and other Prophets. Nay, I ſay further, that the Predictions, Threats, and Promiſes, the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence whereof neceſſarily depends upon futurity, leave certain Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and Idea's on our Minds of thoſe horrible Torments prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the Wicked, and of that glorious Reward and Happineſs deſigned for the Righteous. The Things we underſtand aſſure us of the Truth of thoſe we underſtand not; and when thoſe Places that are clear and evident of themſelves are not ſufficient to render the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intelligible, the Reader ought
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49820:39"/>to humble himſelf, to confeſs his Ignorance Indocility, and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Preſumption to ſtop here. But however, every one may here clearly ſee the <hi>Commands</hi> he is to obey, the <hi>Belief</hi> he is to hold, the <hi>Pattern</hi> of the <hi>Prayers</hi> he is to make, and <hi>Praiſes</hi> he is to return to GOD. And this indeed is all our Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ought to teach us, without their needing to trouble and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex our Minds with Curious Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and loſe both themſelves and others in the Vanity of their own thoughts. But don't we run the hazard of making our ſelves Lyars, if in the leaſt we ſeem to aſſert this Word to be clear and plain, when the Doctors of this Age declare the contrary, and the People believe them? Yes, indeed it is Dark, our SAVIOUR teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies it himſelf; but it is only ſo to the Worldly Wiſe and Learned.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49820:40"/>He thanks his Father, that he has hid theſe things from ſuch, and revealed them to Babes. It is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure to them that periſh, and whom the God of this World has blinded. So that we may confidently affirm that it cannot be apprehended by an Underſtanding meerly Human, and that it muſt be a Divine Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that can conceive a Divine Word. They that have not this Spirit can by no means compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it. None but the Children of God know the Voice of their Father; None but Sheep that of the Shepheard. True it is, and I confeſs, that its exceſſive Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs makes it Dark to many that behold it, and that Noble and true Born <hi>Eagles</hi> only can fix their Eyes upon this Sun, the Light whereof never fails to ſtrike Owls and Bats with Blindneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:49820:40"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p n="23">XXIII. IT is not to be doubted at all but that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of God, the Author of the Univerſal Rebellion and Great Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the World will make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be ador'd in his own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and that conſequently moſt Religions are Worldly and Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical. 'Tis no matter to him by whom, or how they are inſtituted, whether Ignorance, Opinion, Error, or Cuſtom introduces them, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they be equally Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Profane, or whether thoſe who at the firſt worſhipped <hi>Bel</hi> or <hi>Jupiter</hi> do afterward worſhip the <hi>Sun,</hi> the <hi>Moon</hi> and all the <hi>Hoſt</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> nay, and that of <hi>Hell</hi> too. There is no Religion ſo extravagant or ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, which he doth not favour; neither there is, any beſides the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49820:41"/>True, that is diſpleaſing to him. He has firſt heaped Gods upon Gods, introduced their Idols even into the Holy Place, and then found out a way to combate Scripture with Scripture, and raiſed falſe Doctrines from falſe Interpretations. He has made uſe of the Light, only to dazle and blind People; and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd Truth, to cover and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe a Lie, the better to get off his own Impoſtures. He has his <hi>Doctors,</hi> through whoſe Mouths he teaches and diſputes continually. He has his <hi>Votaries,</hi> by whom he expoſes the Pattern of a good and devout Life: Nor doth he want his <hi>Prieſts, Prophets, Holy Men,</hi> or <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</hi> In the mean time, Men don't conſider what Spirit they are led by; And they are often harden'd and delivered up to <hi>Satan;</hi> yea in a manner poſſeſs'd, or at leſt blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him, who have quite other
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49820:41"/>thoughts of themſelves. Beſides they are of ſo preſumptuous and profane a Temper, and have ſo good an Opinion of their Natural Reaſon, that they would fain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his Works, who has formed both themſelves and all things, and paſs their Judgment upon the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Word, with as much peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torineſs, as if it were meerely Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. They are not content with what <hi>Divinity</hi> teaches them, they muſt (forſooth) call in <hi>Philoſophy</hi> to their aſſiſtance, and ſo confound and corrupt both the one and the other; without perceiving that by this means they leave their Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Vocation, and fall under the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantageous ſtate of Heathens. They ſpend their time in exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Curious and Subtle Queſtions, and laying aſide things that are clear, they make it their glory to raiſe Scruples and foment Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49820:42"/>to the diverting (by theſe affected Difficulties) both them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others from the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Truth. Whenſoever it pleaſes them they take Figurative Expreſſions in the Literal Senſe, wreſt thoſe that are <hi>dark</hi> or <hi>doubtful,</hi> and are very dexterous in putting upon equivocal terms, a conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fit for their Turn. They dazle one another's Eyes with ſpecious Arguments, and their weak Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuffers two Contradictories to appear equally probable. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed one would think that their Learning ſerves only to make them more Ignorant, and their Study to accompliſh them in the Art of doubting of every thing; thereby making <hi>Learning</hi> worſe than <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> they are all <hi>Scepticks</hi> by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> only by Name.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:49820:42"/>
               <p n="24">XXIV. Indeed, if there were any certainty in Human Learning, they who preſume to be ſo accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd in the Art of Reaſoning ſhould all agree. But if their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions be ſo various and different, when yet there is but one TRUTH, what does their Science amount to? Their Learning conſiſts in a kind of <hi>Divinity,</hi> that is meerly artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, intricate, thorny, and all full of Quiddities, Inſtances, Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Formalities; which neither the Prophets, nor the Apoſtles, ever thought neceſſary to Salvation, or rather were never acquainted with them; and it were much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for us to be ſo too (after their Examples) than to know them. They are learned in Human Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Chimaera's, ridiculous Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and in every thing that is apt to advance Error, and confound Reaſon by its own Subtilty. All
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49820:43"/>Places ſwarm with vain Bablers, everlaſting Diſputers, who employ their whole ſtudy in the art of gain-ſaying; that let a Man ſay what he will, they may always be ready to contradict him, and are more allarm'd with a falſe <hi>Syllogiſm,</hi> than they are concerned for the <hi>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> or the <hi>Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of <hi>Mankind.</hi> They never come to any Conferences with intent of yielding any thing for the love of Truth, but only to try whether they can gain their Adverſaries by Perſwaſions and Promiſes, or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant them by all manner of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry and cunning Devices. They dread nothing more than to grant one Point, leſt they ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to grant them all; and if any one of them ſhould chance to yield never ſo ſmall a matter, this would preſently ruin his Credit among thoſe of his own Party, and the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49820:43"/>leaſt act of ſincerity would be accounted a crime unpardonable. Wherefore they reſort to thoſe Meetings, well provided with all manner of <hi>School-Stratagems, Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and <hi>Inſtances,</hi> grounded upon certain <hi>Axioms,</hi> or <hi>Maxims</hi> of their own, or others contrivance, and conſtrain all to ſubmit to them, as to Principles of Sovereign Truth, that neither admit of doubts, nor need any evidencing, and on which depends the infallible Conſequence of what they themſelves believe, or would fain perſwade others. Yea, though their Frauds be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, yet they have ſtill ſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour at hand to make them look plauſible, and ſo by a pious Cheat keep the People in their impious Devotions. They are dexterous at taking their advantage. They have the Art of eluding the moſt formal Allegations: They Wire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49820:44"/>the knot of the matter, the ſtate of the Queſtion. They have their Sophiſtical Diſtinctions, their ſet Gloſſes, their Sleights and Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions at their Fingers end; and in Diſputes, as well as in Combates, their ſole intent is to come off Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors. Curſed Wretches! who prefer their own Honour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to that of Religion it ſelf, and who being more ſolicitous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout what they muſt object or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, than what they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, are very little concern'd for their want of <hi>Faith,</hi> provided they do not ſeem to want <hi>Reaſon.</hi> How can we expect, that theſe Men ſhould faithfully explain to us Things dark and abſtruſe, whoſe whole buſineſs it is to darken thoſe that are the moſt clear, and ſo much change the Ordinances of God, that there needs no point of Wit to perceive it; Common ſenſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49820:44"/>and Eye-ſight being ſufficient to make one a competent judge of it? No other fruits can be look'd for either from their Animoſity or Hard-heartedneſs, which render them ſociable only to ſuch as are willing to be inſtructed in their way, or abandon themſelves to their Guidance. For as for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they are no more capable of learning any thing; becauſe they preſume they have learn'd all; and ſo propoſing to themſelves no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the teaching of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, no wonder if they had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſs for <hi>Maſters</hi> of <hi>Error,</hi> than <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="25">XXV. But I hear them already demanding of me, Whether in a matter of this importance, I may without too much preſumption, pretend my Opinion or Judgment to be infallible, or at leaſt better informed, than that of the Doctors
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49820:45"/>themſelves? To which I anſwer, That I will have no other, but that which the moſt clear and intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Words of the Scripture do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſly afford to the moſt ſimple among the People, and which God is pleaſed to reveal to the humble, and hide from the proud. I will have no other, than that which teaches me, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. <hi>That none ought to preſume to know beyond what is Written;</hi> That it is abſolutely forbidden either to add to, or take from it; and that they in vain make profeſſion of honouring God, who honour him only with the Doctrines of Men, and make void his <hi>Law</hi> by their <hi>Tradition.</hi> I will have no other, than that which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands me to avoid profane Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, vain Diſputations, and tedious Contradictions of a Science, falſly ſo call'd, which one cannot follow, without erring from the Faith, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49820:45"/>abandoning one's ſelf to Impiety. I further anſwer, That ſuch Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions ought not in juſtice to be ask'd of thoſe who make uſe of their Senſes and Reaſon only to diſcern the Voice of their Lord and Father, to receive his Commands and obey him, who do not raſhly mix their own Fancies with his Ordinances, and who do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the Scripture, but by it ſelf. 'Tis from the exorbitant Curioſity and ſublime Viſions of theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, <hi>Angelical</hi> and <hi>Seraphick</hi> Doctors, that ſo many extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Opinions ariſe, and not from the innocent Reading of thoſe poor and ſimple Creatures, that in the Word of Eternal Life ſeek for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but a Light to guide them in the Way to Converſion and Salvation. None ever were the Authors of Hereſie, but ſuch as preſume themſelves able to defend
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49820:46"/>it, and who with the ſame Spirit of Pride and Raſhneſs, wherewith they have ſtarted it, are reſolved to maintain it. Theſe are Errors, which none but the Learned are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, and Follies that none but Wiſe Men can commit. The va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of knowing what others know not, of being eſteemed the Author of ſome Novelty, of giving a Name to a Sect, and being the Ring-leader of it; the Dread of Poverty, Thirſt after Riches and Honours, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of pleaſing Great Men, of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving their Favours, flattering their Paſſions, promoting their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, and thereby advancing their own: Theſe are the Secret Articles and chief Myſteries of their <hi>Faith.</hi> They are very willing to quit the Pretenſions of the Soul for the Eaſe of the Body. They are for a Religion that may inſure them a Fortune, and a Conſcience
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49820:46"/>that may yield to Neceſſity. In the mean time, an Error is no ſooner hatcht, bur there are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſome ready to receive and embrace it; and that not out of any Devotion, but from a deſign of forming a new Party, and raiſing Troubles and Diviſions in a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able State. Whole <hi>Europe</hi> is all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dappl'd with Sects, and as it were rent to pieces by the Violence of ſo many Factions; at the ſight whereof <hi>Atheiſts</hi> encreaſe, <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> are confirmed in their Error, <hi>Jews</hi> are ſcandaliz'd, and all equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly harden'd. There is no end of Queſtions; Sometimes about the <hi>Elect,</hi> and at other times about the <hi>Reprobate.</hi> But who are thoſe raſh Perſons, that ſeek for a Reaſon, where ſo great an Apoſtle as St. <hi>Paul</hi> finds no other but the good Will and Pleaſure of God? For my part, I confeſs I cannot won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49820:47"/>enough at them, who with ſo much ingratitude deſpiſe thoſe things, which God has been pleaſed to make known to us, that they may raſhly dive into thoſe, which for a time he would have hid from us. Without too indiſcreet a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and a Curioſity not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly needleſs, but pernicious, I ſhall never diſturb the publick Peace, nor raiſe new Doubts, either about the two <hi>Natures,</hi> the two <hi>Wills,</hi> or <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of JESUS CHRIST, and without a too great Love of my ſelf, I ſhall never pretend to be the COMFORTER with <hi>Montanus,</hi> nor the SAVIOUR of Men, with <hi>Menander.</hi> I will live as a <hi>Believer</hi> with <hi>Believers,</hi> and neither ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize my Brethren by any private Opinion, taken up of my own head, nor by a general undervaluing of the Opinion of others.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:49820:47"/>
               <p n="26">XXVI. So long as the Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Men ſhall introduce into the Church no other Scruples, ſave about the difference of Meat, and have no other Ornaments but Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, and not provoke God's Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie by Graven Images. So long as there ſhall be only ſome ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous Ceremonies, which in the Judgment of many will paſs ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for indifferent, and at other times be thought neceſſary; though indeed an Error, that ſeems but ſmall at firſt, is commonly a ſtep to a greater. So long as its Purity ſhall be, if not altogether ſuch as it might be wiſh'd, yet at leaſt ſuch as is tolerable; I will not depart from its Communion. But I muſt and will withdraw from any Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, where I ſhall be forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form with the outward actions of Superſtition and Idolatry, and pay a Religious Honour and Worſhip,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49820:48"/>not only to Saints and Angels, who are Fellow-Servants with us, but to Wood and Stone; where the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments are not entire, and where the Commandments of God are made void by the Precepts of Men. Neither ſhall I think this is any Schiſm, where there is ſo juſt a reaſon of Separating, and an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of doing otherwiſe. For what elſe ſhould be the meaning or uſe of theſe Words, that command Believers <hi>to go without the Camp,</hi> Heb. 13.13. and to come <hi>out of Babylon,</hi> Rev. 18.4. which going out is not meant of the Spirit only, but of the Body too, ſeeing that both are equally to be conſecrated to the Glory of the Creator? And when we ſhall ſee <hi>the abomination of Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſet in the Holy Place,</hi> Dan. 9.27. muſt not we <hi>fly into the Mountains,</hi> Mat. 24. Or if once Antichriſt be ſeated in the Temple of God, muſt
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49820:48"/>he therefore be obey'd, and what he pleaſeth to injoyn, be called, <hi>the Commandments of the Church?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p n="27">XXVII. WHen therefore I ſaw the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Diviſion of ſo many Sects, which all of them had their Doctors, and ſome of them their Prophets too, I thought, that upon this account the neceſſity of Prayer was very urgent, that there was great occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for us to humble our ſelves, and conſult, not the uncertain Imaginations of Men, but thoſe infallible Rules which God himſelf has laid down. And this I deſired with ſo much the more care to do, becauſe the Word of God tells us, that not only many <hi>Antichriſts</hi> will ariſe in the Church, and one above
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49820:49"/>all the reſt, but alſo that in the time of the Apoſtles themſelves <hi>the Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> began already to put forward, and conſequently muſt be by this time grown to a great height, notwithſtanding their blindneſs, who have no minds to ſee it, and think they are ſafe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough whilſt they can find ſome pretence or other for their wilful Ignorance. I therefore ſuſpected all Religions, which are not purely Evangelical and Divine, which are mixt with Human Inventions, med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with Queſtions too high, and too difficult to be reſolved, and the Controverſy whereof is too ſubtle, and fine-ſpun. I had alſo an ill Opinion of thoſe, that are brought in by the Sword and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, which are ſo little aſſur'd of themſelves, that they are afraid of a Communication with others, and to that end keep their Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49820:49"/>in a Brutiſh Ignorance. In like manner I miſtruſted all thoſe, that comport with the ſeveral intereſts of the World, and put in for a ſhare in its Government, whatever pompous Title of the Church they may aſſume; becauſe they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Order of CHRIST's own Appointment, and raſhly change that into a <hi>Time</hi> of <hi>Glory,</hi> which is appointed for the <hi>Patience</hi> of the <hi>Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="28">XXVIII. Beſides, if we will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve univerſal Experience; Every thing that is under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Men is like them, ſubject to Alteration, Mutability, and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and ſoon or late follows the Way of their Inconſtancy. Children do not willingly continue in their Fathers, or at leaſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors Belief; and Faith is not he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary, as the Title of a Family or an Eſtate is. For the moſt part
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49820:50"/>they have nothing left of it, but an outward Profeſſion, to which they being no otherwiſe engaged but by Birth or Cuſtom, they ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily abandon what their depraved Nature neither incline them to know, or love; ſo that if they have begun with good and ſound Doctrine, a bad one is their Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at laſt. Thus we ſee that the purity of the Goſpel, whereſoever it hath been received, has been ſeldom tranſmitted to the third Generation: and the Apoſtles were yet alive, when in the very Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es they had planted, Error crept in inſenſibly into the room of Truth. God threaten'd them already with the removal of their Candleſtick; giving them to underſtand, that Faith was no more the peculiar Priviledge of any one Place, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or People, and that the Church being become Univerſal, could not
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49820:50"/>be ſubjected to the Juriſdiction of one King only, or the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one ſingle Prieſt. 'Tis in vain for Men to pretend to lay the Foundation of a permanent State, or to find a Supreme Good here in this Life; They are not able to bear Proſperity long, and the ſureſt way to undo them, is to grant them their deſires. If our firſt Parents, though in the State of Innocency, could not among the Flowers and Fruits of a moſt pleaſant and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Garden reſiſt the ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Evil Spirit,</hi> who to tempt them, took no other Form, than that of a <hi>Serpent,</hi> nor offer'd any thing but an <hi>Apple;</hi> how is it poſſible for thoſe who are Sinners by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to withſtand him, eſpecially when he transforms himſelf into an <hi>Angel</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> and offers them all the advantages their Hearts can deſire? It is indeed in a Paradiſe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49820:51"/>of Pleaſures, that the Devil, for the moſt part, tempts Men, to precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate them into Hell; and on the other hand, it is in a Hell of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows and Afflictions, that God trys them in order to raiſe them up to the Glory of Paradiſe. Riches are ſo hurtful to thoſe that poſſeſs them, that like a heavy Burthen, they hinder them from mounting up to Heaven. And ſo incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are they with the Profeſſion of the Goſpel, that even he to whom they all belong, and who could uſe them without the leaſt abuſe, did of his own accord become <hi>Poor,</hi> that he might trace us the way of <hi>Eternal Salvation,</hi> and by his <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty</hi> we might be made <hi>Rich.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, all good Men do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge what is confirmed by Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Bountiful Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Emperors, and the free Gifts of Lords and Ladies have proved
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49820:51"/>the moſt dangerous Poiſon, that could ever have been handed to the Church; That from that time Piety began to grow cold, and make room for the Cares of this World, and that all Chriſtian Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues were ſoon choak'd by great Plenty and Luxury. All thoſe great Benefactors, who are ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely commended to us, plainly ſhew'd, that they were not through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informed of the Will of our SAVIOUR, nor of the true Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Miniſters, when they thus inriched them with Temporal Eſtates, and made of them ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Members and Favourers of the Kingdom of this World. This great Wealth that flow'd in upon them, all on a Sudden, was but an ill omen to the Faithful, who eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly judged that for the future none but the Ambitious, Covetous, Wicked, and Profligate could aſpire
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49820:52"/>to any Office in the Church, and that ſhe was going to be reduced to that extream Miſery, as not to be governed by any, but by her worſt Enemies.</p>
               <p n="29">XXIX. From that time, the Corruption has (by a ſtrange Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Heaven) grown to this height, that the <hi>Clergy</hi> are grown worſe than the <hi>Laity.</hi> They have received from Men that Authority, which in their ſtation they ſhould receive from none but God, and if they have taken any care about Spiritual Things, it was not to <hi>ſerve,</hi> but to <hi>command,</hi> to advance themſelves to the Higheſt Dignities, and to be made <hi>Biſhops</hi> over other <hi>Biſhops.</hi> They have imitated him, who deſpiſing a Common Joy with the other Angels, had the boldneſs to attempt the raiſing himſelf to the higheſt Pitch of Singularity and Superiority, ſaying in his
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49820:52"/>Heart, <hi>I will ſet up my Throne above the Stars, and be like the Moſt High.</hi> Inſtead of confining themſelves to the Obſervation of that true Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, which God had inſtitued and preſcribed himſelf, they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed its Simplicity, would not away with any Devotions, but ſuch as were Pompous and Dazling, or if you'l have it in their own Words, they have <hi>hallowed the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of Paganiſm,</hi> by admitting them into the Church. They could not endure the Purity of the Goſpel-Doctrine, without adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating and diſguiſing it a thouſand ways; and to that end, have choſen Doctors and Teachers after their own fancies: They have ſtarted ſubtle Queſtions, which they that teach or preach them, often under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand no better, than their Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, however full of ſenſe they may appear, when utter'd from an
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49820:53"/>Eloquent Mouth, wherewith both the one and the other ſeem equally ſatisfied. We have ſeen wretched Worms, that were but a while ſince come out of the Duſt, and ready to return to it again, have the inſolence to aſſume the Title of God, and dare to command An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, as their Uſhers, and diſpoſe of Heaven and Hell, as if they were their own Demain. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, what likelihood is there for them to be the infallible Truſtees of God's Will, and the juſt Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires of the Faith of the World, who owe their Promotion only to Bought Voices, Bribes, Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Promiſes, Threats, Factious Combinations, Contracts, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacies? What Patience would not be tired, to ſee ſuch, as are ſway'd by no other Spirit, than that of ſelf-intereſt, who make of the <hi>Church</hi> a <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Merchandiſe,</hi> and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49820:53"/>a <hi>Den</hi> of <hi>Thieves,</hi> ſhould yet be ſteel'd to that exceſs of Impiety, as to render the Holy Ghoſt not an Accomplice, but a Principal in their Crimes? Now if after all the Credit they have in Heaven, they would ſhew themſelves a little leſs concerned for their Earthly Pelf, perhaps one might doubt, whether their Authority did not (as they pretend it does) run parallel with the Divine. But as they are like Lions for cruelty and violence, ſo are they like Leeches for Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and there is no end of their new Contrivances for the alluring of Men to make vaſt Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the inſatiable Idol they Worſhip. For to paſs by ſo many <hi>Excommunications, Interdictions, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, Appeals, Suits,</hi> and <hi>Exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> under the pretext of ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a War againſt the Enemies of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> There is no end with
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49820:54"/>their <hi>Reverſions</hi> of <hi>Benefices, Firſt Fruits, Bulls, Indulgences, Canons, Caſes</hi> of <hi>Conſcience, Pardons, Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> both of <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> and <hi>Supererogatory Satisfactions.</hi> All which Inventions make not Sins <hi>Venial,</hi> except it be by making them <hi>Venal;</hi> they expoſe Prayers, Sacraments, Heaven, and God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſale, and proſtitute them to the higheſt Bidder. Horrid Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions! that turn <hi>Simon Peter</hi> into a <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and make, as far as in them lies, a <hi>Tyrant</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Hirelings</hi> and <hi>Brokers</hi> of his <hi>Apoſtles!</hi> What a goodly Divinity is this! That all, who have wherewith to pay, how heinons ſoever their Sins be, may be in a moment, deliver'd from the pains of Hell, or at leaſt from thoſe of Purgatory; which others muſt ſwelter through for ſome thouſands of Years, unleſs perhaps, <hi>Poverty,</hi> voluntary, or per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>force;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49820:54"/>
                  <hi>Faſtings,</hi> to that exceſs as to be their own Murtherers; <hi>Naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Hair-Cloth</hi> and <hi>Scourges</hi> do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve them thence! But beſides this Spiritual Merchandizing and Selling of every thing that is Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred; by what Divine Inſpiration are they authoriz'd to abſolve Men from their Oaths of Allegiance, and diſcharge them of their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Duty to their Lawful Kings and Princes, whom they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endeavour to terrifie with their Thunderbolts, than to make them truly devout? or can that horrid and abominable Inquiſition, which makes them ſtop their Ears to the juſt Remonſtrances of thoſe that long for a Reformation, be called an Imitation of the <hi>Tenderneſs</hi> and <hi>Bowels</hi> of our SAVIOUR, and not rather of the <hi>Cruelty</hi> of <hi>Herod,</hi> who cauſed ſo many Innocent Babes to be be put to Death, for fear on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49820:55"/>of miſſing Him who was Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence it ſon.</p>
               <p n="30">XXX. O GOD! how long wilt thou bear with the Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Children of Pride, to whom Religion ſerves but for a Cloak and a Pretext, and who make uſe of thy Name only to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice people to give more willingly? How long wilt thou ſuffer that horrid Scandal, which on their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thoſe Nations do receive, with whom there ſtill remains at leaſt ſome Shadow of Reſpect for that Law thou didſt pronounce thy ſelf; and who ſeeing the Objects of thy Jealouſie, thoſe Images ſet up in Churches, thoſe Feſtivals appointed in honour of them, and that Religious Service paid to them, fancy all this is done by the command of thy CHRIST, and that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> do indeed Worſhip as many <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women,</hi> as the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49820:55"/>Heathens ever did <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſes!</hi> How long wilt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear deſtroying with the Breath of thy Mouth, all thoſe who with ſo much inſolence and hypocriſie thus impoſe upon the People by their juggling Deluſions, which both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts</hi> flock to ſee, that they may diſcover the cheat of them, and be confirmed in their averſion to that Religion that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to juſtifie and maintain it ſelf by ſuch lying Miracles! For redreſs of which abuſes there is no other way but to apply our ſelves to thy Supream Power; for it is in vain for us to think of working upon ſuch as will not be cur'd of the good Opinion they have taken up of themſelves, who think they are ſo well endowed by Heaven, that they excell all others in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe, that they have no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions but what are the Dictates
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49820:56"/>of Reaſon, nor no impreſſions but what they have received from the Mouth of Truth. If the <hi>Pagans</hi> did ſo ſtrongly oppoſe the Goſpel, and the Knowledge of the TRUE GOD, when preached to them, who had no other <hi>Gods</hi> but ſuch as Men had made, what reſiſtance may not we expect from them who aſſume to themſelves GOD's own <hi>Authority,</hi> who think they are in poſſeſſion of all Right and Power both Divine and Humane, who imagine that from henceforth to the end of the World, all Might is given them in Heaven and on Earth, and who under the Name of the <hi>Church,</hi> make all manner of Errors to be applauded, and put off their Cheats and Impoſtures without either fear or ſhame? Princes, who could at firſt have prevented thoſe Abuſes, tolerated them, through what irreligious
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49820:56"/>Prudence I know not; whether it was that they wanted Light to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern them, or that the Cares of the World, and of their Eſtates obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them to diſſemble their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or whether they were in ſome ſort forced to yield to the Decree of Heaven, and could not but in vain oppoſe themſelves againſt the fulfilling of what the Prophets had foretold. Prophecies which having long ſince repreſented things to us juſt as now we ſee them, render ſo many Doctors inexcuſable, who through fear or hope held their Peace, and with a faithleſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable Silence ſtrengthned that which they might have weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a juſt Contradiction and Oppoſition; Nay, they have been obſerved to be the moſt induſtrious in the Defence of that Error, which they could once have buried under an Eternal Condemnation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:49820:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p n="31">XXXI. THere is no <hi>Tyrant</hi> that makes himſelf to be better obey'd than <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in <hi>Religion:</hi> It is ſo much the more abſolute, by how much the more it influences and engages the Conſcience, and out of fear of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amiſs, obliges them to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue that homage they have begun to pay to it. Which plainly ſhews that notwithſtanding the preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that attends Men, and the good Opinion they have of their own Wit, they are for all that for the moſt part ſo weak by Nature, that one would take their Soul not to be derived from Heaven, but purely Animal, and to have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Form, than that which Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction has given it. They are ſo much by aſs'd by their Birth, Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49820:57"/>and Company, that the firſt that poſſeſſes them carries them away, and does not give them leave to believe any thing but what they have been once perſwaded of. Therefore I have, as much as in me lies, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated my ſelf from my ſelf, that is to ſay, from thoſe impreſſions I had received in my Youth; I have conſider'd them, as foreign and remote, that ſo, <hi>Truth</hi> might be the ſole Object of my <hi>Faith,</hi> and that <hi>Cuſtom</hi> in me might exerciſe no <hi>Tyranny</hi> over my <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Beſides I always conſidered that none could ſay he really was a Man, who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd himſelf to be carried away with the Stream of the World, who was not in ſome meaſure above the Councils that were given him, and had ſo little courage as not to make uſe of his own Judgment, but yielded it a Slave to Common
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49820:58"/>Errors. Yet as moſt Men approve no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what they have been us'd to and judge of every thing accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as Cuſtom has render'd it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar to them; ſo whenever they have contracted any ill habit, the Remedy is extreamly difficult; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Faculties are ſeized, and it muſt be a powerful Endeavour that can deliver them from it. They grow up and are formed with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Impreſſions,</hi> which become ſo con-natural to them, that they make up the chief part of their <hi>Reaſon;</hi> They have been taught no other <hi>Science;</hi> they underſtand no other <hi>Language,</hi> and unleſs they be <hi>born again,</hi> or have their <hi>Nature</hi> chang'd, they cannot alter their <hi>Belief.</hi> They do not perceive that inſtead of ſtanding up for the <hi>Truth,</hi> they undertake the Defence of the firſt Opinion, they have receiv'd, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out examining whether it be as
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49820:58"/>true as it is favourable, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not grounded upon meer Prejudices, ſpecious Pretences, Likelihoods, Conjectures, and Worldly Conſiderations. They don't obſerve that all Sects pretend the ſame Advantages, that all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies have their Followers, who defend them with a like Zeal, and have their Doctors, who think themſelves no ways inferior to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whether in Point of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Learning. They do not perceive that they are ſmoothly carried away by the ſtream of Self-Love, which perſwades them that they are very different from others of their kind; that they can pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate things better, and that they enjoy the Divine Light, whilſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have ſcarcely that which is Humane. According to their ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, there is nothing ſo true, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo eaſie to comprehend, as
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49820:59"/>that which they believe; the Proof of it is clear and evident, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration certain and infallible, and he that does not underſtand it, can underſtand nothing at all: Reaſon is always on their ſide, and Error and Obſtinacy the portion of their Adverſaries. What Blind Fury, what Madneſs, what Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption hinders them from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that thoſe they are ſo much aſtoniſh'd at, look upon them with equal aſtoniſhment; that they appear ridiculous to them they laugh at, and that they for whom they make but a ſhew of pity, are really and in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt moved with pity towards them? Should not they, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the uncertainty of things, and the miſerable condition of Man's Mind, have recourſe to uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Maxims, and ſtand firm to the Ordinances of the Supream
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49820:59"/>Law-giver, who expreſly ferbids to depart therefrom, and turn ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Right or to the Left?</p>
               <p n="32">XXXII. But ſo far are they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs'd with what the World of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to them, and the Cares of this Life have ſo blinded their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they will not enquire about any Principle, nor judge that neither Space of Time, nor Priviledge of Places, nor any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Conſiderations whatſoever can give any preſcription againſt <hi>Truth.</hi> Beſides this, they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of their Parents Faith; by Domeſtick Examples, by the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and by Antiquity it ſelf; which may be attributed to an Error that has inſenſibly crept-in, and by proceſs of time taken en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe; and at length grown to ſuch a height and power, that thoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies who have ventur'd to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it, have been bruis'd or cruſh'd
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49820:60"/>by it. It is a hard thing, without doubt, for a Man to pronounce a Sentence of Condemnation againſt his own Country and Prince; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Anceſtors, Parents, and Friends, and againſt his own Teachers; But the caſe here is to rid and undeceive ones ſelf of the Errors of all Human Imaginations; to juſtifie the <hi>Truth</hi> againſt the falſe Teſtimonies of ſo many Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; to cure the diſeaſes of a Dying Life; to ſeek one Sovereign Good and Felicity, and to aſſent to his Word, who ſays, <hi>That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever loves Father or Mother, or any thing elſe more than him, is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of him.</hi> But for all this they are reſolved to follow the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of ſo many Honeſt Men they alledge; not conſidering that the <hi>Turks</hi> can at leaſt ſay as much; that the <hi>Pagans</hi> could ſay yet more; and they had rather keep
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49820:60"/>to thoſe ill choſen Principles, than examine the beſt Doctrine that can be propoſed to them. Beſides, they are, as it were, liſted and made Slaves, to live and dye under the Tyranny of certain Leaders, who pretend they cannot err, and ſay, that they have the Spirit of God aſſiſting in their Conſiſtories, and directing them in all their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions; that they are the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of a Sovereign Court, and over and above this, know how to reconcile Religion with the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages and Pleaſures of this World. This is a thing they eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffer themſelves to be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of, as being more agreeable to their humour, and ſubſervient to their Deſigns. They gladly lend an ear to Calumny; take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to ſee them convinc'd of <hi>Error,</hi> who ſpeak for the <hi>Truth,</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they ſuſpect, and dare not ſo
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49820:61"/>much as caſt an Eye towards it, leſt being taken with its tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Beauty, they ſhould be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd to follow it, and undergo ſome juſt ſeverities and hardſhips, which their wilful Humours could never yield to. They are willingly ignorant of thoſe Maxims, they have no mind to practice, as find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome kind of quiet in this <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;</hi> and are loath to receive a <hi>Law,</hi> how juſt ſoever it be, that may force their <hi>Liberty.</hi> For, the truth is, that Afflictions make up a great part of the Profeſſion of the Goſpel, is enough to deter World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men from it. They had rather yield to the ſwift Stream that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries them along, than to row a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; They had rather be drou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in a ſweet Sleep full of pleaſant Dreams, than hear their trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Voice, who awake them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to afflict them. O brutiſh ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity!
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49820:61"/>O viſible Obſtinacy! What? muſt then <hi>Vices</hi> and <hi>Errors,</hi> that are grown Publick, loſe their Name, and acquire that of <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom?</hi> and muſt <hi>Cuſtom</hi> have ſo much Power over Men, as to hinder them from being reaſonable Creatures? But who doubts but that thoſe who are by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaid to be Drunk, are ſo far depriv'd of their Senſes and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as to take <hi>Falſhood</hi> for <hi>Truth,</hi> and not to perceive what their Eyes ſee? Who doubts but that they are like thoſe People, who had ſo uſed themſelves to <hi>Poiſon,</hi> that at laſt it ſerved them inſtead of <hi>Food?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="33">XXXIII. In the mean time they have reduced all Religion to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Traditions, and Superſtitions; Neither Reaſon nor Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are once call'd in to give their Verdict in the caſe; and I do not
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49820:62"/>know by what Error, or how it is come to paſs, that moſt Men, who are curious of all other <hi>Sciences,</hi> do not ſo much as inquire into <hi>that</hi> which is the moſt neceſſary. They, with the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> have no other <hi>Knowledge</hi> of GOD, but ſuch as is obſcure, idle, empty, fruitleſs, and dead; and had they been born among the <hi>Turks,</hi> they would have been of the ſame Belief with them, having nothing but an Acquired Faith, that depends only upon Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, which never ſaved any Man. This Faith they have in common, both with the Devils and wicked Men, who (as well as they) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that God is Almighty; that he has created the World and ſent his Son, the whole Myſtery of whoſe Birth, Life, and Death they believe, and yet muſt not pretend to have any ſhare in his Kingdom and Glory. It is a thing that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49820:62"/>both our Pity, and our Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, to ſee the indiſcreet zeal of a People, who pray they know not what; who feed themſelves with Shews, and ſuffer themſelves to be led away by ſuch Teachers as make them thirſt more after their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's Blood, than his Salvation. A People impoſed upon, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded with vain Things, who fancy God is better pleaſed in one Place than in another, and who go to ſeek among Strangers what they might as well find in the midſt of themſelves. An ignorant and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking People, that without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what they do, under the Goſpel revive <hi>Judaiſm,</hi> in direct oppoſition to the Word, which ſaith, <hi>That the hour is come when the true Worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> What can Places or Pilgrimages conduce to this? Or all thoſe Religious
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49820:63"/>Services, which are valued only for their Number, not for their Quality, and the performance whereof is impoſed neither out of Piety, nor Faith, but as certain Tasks they put upon themſelves, and certain Numbers which they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute ſome Virtue to, and do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, much after the ſame manner as Magicians do? Devotions full of Superſtition, Scruples, and Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, as of Men that are afraid to know the Truth, and to whom the Light is hurtful, who conceive nothing of the true Religion but what is told them by the very Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of it, who can entertain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better for it than hatred and calumny; always repreſenting it in the moſt hideous ſhape they can imagine. Indeed, it is an eaſie matter to perſwade them any thing, who have already been perſwaded to that blind Obedience, to which
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49820:63"/>they give their conſent with as much Unmanlineſs and Senſeleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as if they ſhould ſay, <hi>I will be ſtupid, I will be ſenſible of nothing.</hi> For if once they ſay they will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Church, they contradict themſelves, and own that they will follow what they know. Now how many things muſt a Man know to be able to diſcern the falſe Church from the true? To what purpoſe is Blind Obedience in them whom God has endu'd with Reaſon, and after that given them his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances with an expreſs Command to Parents <hi>to teach their Children the ſame,</hi> and to all, <hi>to ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> which alone plainly ſhew the <hi>Way</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Heaven?</hi> But how ſhould thoſe inſtruct o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who are ſo ill inſtructed themſelves, who for a juſt Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for worſhipping things inani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, are ſtruck with ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49820:64"/>hardneſs, that to ask them for Advice or Anſwers, would be the ſame as to conſult Marble.</p>
               <p n="34">XXXIV. Ye Blind, don't you perceive that you loſe your Senſes only by applying your ſelves too much to things inſenſible? Don't you ſee that Reaſon it ſelf makes you inferior to the Object of your Adoration, and that your wicked inclinations have made you leſs then the Work of your own hands? O ye Fools, leave <hi>Puppets</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies</hi> for Children; they are ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for an Age that can exert <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> Ye are no leſs guilty than the Atheiſts; for with them you annihilate the Deity, when you fix the form thereof to any Matter whatſoever, and when you repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Him, who is a Spirit by a piece of Wood or Stone, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he has ſaid, with ſo much jealouſie, <hi>To what will ye liken me?</hi>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:49820:64"/>Thus you raſhly make him that has made you, and through an unaccountable inſolence and ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, you ſeem to endeavour to render him ridiculous, by giving him Eyes that cannot ſee, Ears that cannot hear, Hands that cannot handle, and Feet that cannot walk. Perhaps you think your good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention will be an Excuſe for your Ignorance; You go as you are led, and whatever you do, you believe you do God Service, even when you afflict the Faithful, and put them to Death. Ye Hypocrites, know that numerous Abuſes are ready to croud in under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Good Intentions, which, if they be not grounded upon the Word of God, are but ſo many Sins. Thus the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> juſtly under-went the Puniſhment due to their Raſhneſs, who whilſt they were worſhipping the Golden Calf,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49820:65"/>thought they did celebrate a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Feaſt to the Lrod, Thus <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> ſtir'd up God's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and the Fire that conſumed them, though they had no other Intention but to offer up Perfumes and incenſe to him. Thus <hi>Uzzah</hi> was immediately ſtruck Dead for having ſtretched forth his hand to the Ark, which ſeemed ready to fall; though he had no other deſign than to keep it up. If good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions only are ſufficient to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Men, the <hi>Jews,</hi> Enemies of CHRIST, were not guilty; St. <hi>Paul</hi> giving them this Teſtimony, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.2. <hi>That they had the zeal of God.</hi> By this means, that is, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of Good Intentions, many unjuſt Sentences might be juſtified, many Murthers and Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacres ranked among Pious Works; all Religions might bring us to Heaven, and almoſt all Men would be ſaved.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:49820:65"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p n="35">XXXV. THerefore in an Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe or Practice, wherein Men have received ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Inſtructions and inviolable Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, 'tis in vain for them to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or pretend Good Intentions, which can have no place but in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. There is no need of ſeeking for new Counſels or Advice in a matter in which there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doubts nor danger, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ableſt Profeſſors and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have no other Authority than to cauſe Men carefully to obſerve the Divine Ordinances; And in this Senſe it is, that the Church cannot err. So that they who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive both themſelves and others with theſe vain Excuſes, are as ſo many Hypocrites that never did ſeriouſly ſet their Hearts upon Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:49820:66"/>Things, aiming at nothing elſe but to make an advantage of the Trade and Commerce of the World. I have conſidered them under all their Circumſtances; and whether it be becauſe the Scripture has foretold it, or Experience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd it, I find that Great Men have ſeldom any ſenſe of true Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in them, that they ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be carried away more by Faction than by Reaſon, and like no Counſels better than ſuch as are favourable to their Worldly Ends. They make uſe of Religion as a Cloak to their boundleſs Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and many conſpire againſt their own Princes or the Government, and are hatching Helliſh Deſigns under the ſpecious Pretence of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating (forſooth) the Catholick Faith. From their very infancy they have thoſe that puff them up with Pride, and egg them on
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49820:66"/>to a falſe Generoſity. They are rarely entertain'd with any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe about the Knowledge of God; unleſs it be at a Sermon, which they never frequent but with reluctancy and impatience; They look upon their Converſation as rude, uncouth, and tedious, who ſpeak to them of Religion and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. They have no Deſire for that they know not; or if any one of them pretend to have ſome glimpſe of that knowledge, they are only Surmiſes and Probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, wherewith they fill their heads, and perſwade themſelves that things are really ſo as their Paſſion makes them to fancy. It were raſhneſs to contradict them: for being poſſeſs'd of Fortune and Power, they think they cannot want Senſe and Reaſon; They joyn Authority to their Opinion, and pronounce Sentences from which
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49820:67"/>there is no Appeal. They can hardly abide any Company, but ſuch as indulge their Self-Love, nor any Diſcourſes that do not flatter their humours and idle ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations. They are altogether vain in their Words and Thoughts; they ſuffer themſelves to be delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded only with outward Show and Appearances, and to that Degree pleaſe themſelves with looks and colours, that they would reject the beſt things in the World, if they were convey'd to them by weak or mean Inſtruments. They would never have received the Law from the Mouth of <hi>Moſes,</hi> becauſe of his impediment in his Spheeh. Truth muſt be preſented to them in a fine Dreſs, and ſumptuouſly adorned, that is with the artifice of Lies, and unleſs a Man be Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and his diſcourſe Floriſh'd, he muſt never think to perſwade
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49820:67"/>them any thing, were it a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from God himſelf. Who if at any time he thinks fit to ſend his Meſſengers to them, and they be taken from the meaneſt of the People, from among Shepheards and Fiſhermen, they will paſs the ſame Judgment upon them, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did on the Apoſtles, whom they look'd upon as worſe than abominable, and the very off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of Men, if they do not proceed to ſtone and murther, or to impriſon and baniſh them.</p>
               <p n="36">XXXVI. There is in the World a ſeeming Wiſdom, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but an habit of making Faces, and a refin'd piece of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, by which Men deceive one another, ſo that their whole Life is but a continual <hi>Maſquerade</hi> or <hi>Comedy,</hi> where every one perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates another than himſelf, and affects nothing more than to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:49820:68"/>what he is not. This incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Phrenzy, to which they give the Name of <hi>Prudentials,</hi> does ſo much diſturb their Underſtanding, and feed them with ſo many fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Chimaera's, that it renders them incapable of apprehending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Divine Truth. They only bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and concern themſelves about things that are periſhable, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that they heap up Riches only for ſuch as will one day ſquander them away, and are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous only to make Prodigals and Luxurious. What Parents are theſe, who whether they indulge their Children at home, or ſend them to a Monaſtry, ſeem equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have reſolved their Ruin, who for fear of wanting wherewith to pamper the Vanity of thoſe they keep with them, rob the other of their lawful Inheritance, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they know what Luſt or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:49820:68"/>is, under pretence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voting them to God, inhumanely ſacrifice them to their ambitious Avarice! O Degenerate Prudence! which makes the Mind become a Slave to the Body! Which makes Men only dexterous to ſhun their Sovereign Good! How ingenious to deſtroy, and cunning to deceive themſelves! It was this, made our Firſt Parents forfeit the Bleſſed State they enjoy'd in Paradiſe, and which by making Man fancy a thouſand Ways of ordering his Life, has filled the World with impious Superſtitions, Idolatries, Sects, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, and Religions. This is it that has perſecuted the <hi>Saints,</hi> cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified our SAVIOUR, and uſed all its endeavours for the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Defence of ſeveral <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts,</hi> whoſe Kingdom was to be of this World. It is this Prudence, falſly ſo called, that continually
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:49820:69"/>reſiſts and contradicts the Holy Ghoſt, and is ſo daring as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe contrary to the expreſs Word of God, either by wreſting the Meaning of it, or leaving out ſome Expreſſions, where they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo well alter'd and diſguis'd, as not to appear quite oppoſite to it. In ſhort, it is this Prudence, that has the Art of making every thing ſuit with its own intereſt, which ſeeing the Divine Service perform'd in an unknown Tongue (whereby People are kept in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) Prayers diverted from the Creator to the Creature, Images carried upon Men's Shoulders, and celebrated with Hymns, and many ſuch like or worſe actions, would fain make them paſs for ſlight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies, or things altogether indifferent.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:49820:69"/>
               <p n="37">XXXVII. Of all the Hypocrites in the World, they are the moſt dangerous, who cover themſelves with the Cloak of Religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none can with more eaſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon others than thoſe that make profeſſion of Holineſs, and who have the vogue of never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving any. Some of them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear of a ſweet and mild Temper, and others are as ſevere: but all of them equally endeavour to put a gloſs on their own Virtue. If their ſeeming Sweetneſs betrays us, their Severity deſpiſes us, and the high eſteem they have for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, makes them have but a very mean one for their Neighbours. They have got the art of appearing for a while what their Profeſſion and Character oblige them to be. But this forced Good Nature and affected Condeſcenſion laſts no longer than their Intereſts and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:49820:70"/>are not thwarted. For though they ſeem to be very tame, yet they cannot play the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeits long, for Nature damm'd up will at laſt take its courſe with more violence; If you do provoke them never ſo little, they will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover thoſe Lions and Tigers they kept hidden under an Human Figure; and, if you will believe them, their Anger is the pure effect of Right Reaſon, and their Crimes are more juſt than the beſt Actions of other Men. If Men think them to be Saints, they eaſily believe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſuch, and lay claim to the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as the true Reward of their falſe Devotion. Indeed this Shadow of Piety, or rather, Flaſhing Zeal has often ſurpriz'd me, till I conſider'd that all Nations have their <hi>Zealots,</hi> and that ours cannot equal the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Auſterity of the <hi>Cynicks, Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoreans, Hierophantes,</hi> or <hi>Gymno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophiſts.</hi>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:49820:70"/>And there is, beſides, this difference between them, that thoſe miſerable Heathens worſhipp'd <hi>Daemons,</hi> as they would be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd; but theſe worſhip the True God, in a way directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to his Commands. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, who knows upon what grounds Men reſolve for Devotion; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not from ſome Natural Inclination, which they have in common with the Barbarians and Infidels, or out of Pride and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, as if the State and Publick Affairs ſtood in need of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Honeſty? None of them will do a Virtuous Action for Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues ſake; they have all By-ends, and thoſe whom the fear of Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot keep in their Duty, are reſtrain'd by the Hope of Riches and Honours. Many of them have the patience to diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble their Malice, till they have
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:49820:71"/>compaſs'd their Deſigns; but when they can mount no higher, and want neither Votes nor Favour to give them a further Lift, they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it. To arrive to this pitch them employ all manner of artifice. They talk like Saints, write good Books, and preach ſome Truths; and have often forc'd me to expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate, <hi>Who has put the Divine Word into the Mouths of theſe Men, and made us alſo in our Days find</hi> Saul <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Prophets?</hi> I have with care and attention heard their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which want neither Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Places, profound Thoughts, nor Tragical Paſſions, more fit for the <hi>Stage</hi> than the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> nor any of all the Colours that the Art of moving and pleaſing can contribute to them: But whatever good Leſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons they may mix with them, they ſtill keep firm to their rotten Foundation; and foraſmuch as
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:49820:71"/>they have no other aim but of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Benefices, trucking them for others, and heaping Dignities upon Dignities, they preach <hi>Chriſt</hi> out of ſtrife and emulation only, and bear witneſs to him much like thoſe evil Spirits, who confeſs'd that he was the Son of God, and were no ſooner come out of one Body but preſently begg'd leave to go into others. And as if it were but a ſmall thing for them to diſguiſe themſelves to Men, even to the diſſembling of their very diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, they make Profeſſion of a manifeſt and publick Hypocriſie toward God: For ſo I call that outſide and ſhow-worſhip, that painted Devotion, by which Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are amaz'd with the eying of <hi>Geſtures,</hi> hearing of <hi>Sounds,</hi> and pronouncing of <hi>Words,</hi> they do not at all underſtand.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:49820:72"/>
               <p n="38">XXXVIII. Yet we ſee with what earneſtneſs they briſtle up for the Defence of what they know not, and are willing to be ſtill ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of. They are charmed with a ſeeming Good; and true Religion appears to them but a poor cold thing, in compariſon of the more gay and pompous My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Superſtition. Wretched Superſtition! which makes it ſelf to be follow'd with Paſſion, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fury, by ſo many weak Minds and ſilly Women, that are called Devout, and are exactly of the ſame Nature with thoſe that could not be quiet till they had ſtirred up a Sedition againſt thoſe two Holy Apoſtles <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas.</hi> They frame to themſelves a very difficult God, whom nothing can ſatisfie, and with whom one has never done: From whence ariſe their raſh Vows, Pilgrimages, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:49820:72"/>delivered in Tale, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Repititions. They ſpend more time in the Church, than in their Houſes, whither they never return but to grieve and vex their Families, and never ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves merry amongſt them, but when they ſubmit to their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and conſent to their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Faſts. Under a ſhew of great Piety they make way for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Courts of Kings, and the greateſt and richeſt Houſes, where ſome deſire them, and others ſuffer them, many are troubled with them, complain of them, defie them, and look upon them as the worſt of the World, and the beſt judgments commonly afford them the worſt teſtimony. They ſee well enough that they are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, of little judgment, and timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, full of Jealouſies, Doubts, and Scruples; that upon very ſlight
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:49820:73"/>occaſions they are ſometimes ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed into admiration, and at other times ſeiz'd with horror: That they are eaſily provoked, the leaſt thing troubles and diſquiets them, and are amaz'd at any Event above their capacity. Every thing is to them a proof of what they have a mind to believe, and Legerdemain, Juggling Tricks, Slights, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions are by them look'd upon as true Miracles. You may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them what you will about things of remote Countries, and make them eſteem Traſh for the greateſt Rarities: They often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere that upon the faith of an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor, which was gathered on their own Mountains, or found on their Shores, as if it came from Mounr <hi>Libanon,</hi> from the Banks of the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> or from the moſt Sacred Places of <hi>Paleſtina.</hi> Sure Mount <hi>Calvary</hi> muſt be quite le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:49820:73"/>by this time, or at leaſt is nothing but Earth and Duſt; all the Stones even to the leaſt Peb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, having been pick'd up long ſince for Holy Things and Relicks, to adorn the <hi>Oratories</hi> of an infinite Number of Virgins, who would think they gave but a very ill proof of their good Education, if they did not ſhew themſelves more Superſtitious than their Mothers.</p>
               <p n="39">XXXIX. All theſe abuſes are well enough known to many, who for all that cannot hinder them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves either from condemning, or from following them; and whoſe <hi>Works</hi> give their <hi>Words</hi> the Lye. For if any Weakneſs keep them back, and they deſire to be ſecret Diſciples of JESUS CHRIST, why don't they contribute to the relief of the poor Members of his Church? Or, if they cannot yet make any great ſhew of their zeal, why (at
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:49820:74"/>leaſt) do they not take care that their Idolatry may not appear at all? But preſs them a little upon this Point, and you will make the Venom guſh out. They preſently fall into a paſſion, grow very angry, and uſe the Authority they have of impoſing Silence; and diſcover their Hypocriſy. <hi>You are</hi> (ſay they) <hi>not above an hundred years ſtanding; You are Schiſmaticks; Why did you leave the Church?</hi> But the Fops ſhould add, <hi>You will not worſhip that which is lifted up at the Altar, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that a piece of Bread is made your God. You will not proſtrate your ſelves before the Likeneſs of any thing that is in Heaven above, or on the Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath; and you are ſcandalized at the Submiſſion of thoſe People who run a whoring after Shrines and Images with Himns of Devotion and Praiſe. You are ſo preſumptuous, as that you will needs receive the Sacrament whole, and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:49820:74"/>in both kinds, according to</hi> CHRIST's Inſtitution, <hi>and are not contented with that ſhare thereof which the</hi> Church <hi>has thought ſufficient for you. You will underſtand the</hi> Word <hi>which</hi> GOD <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects to you, the</hi> Prayers <hi>you put up, and the whole</hi> Service <hi>you are bound to render to him. In a word, you will not ſubmit your ſelves to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Learned, the Examples of Magiſtrates and Princes, and will allow nothing to Tradition or Cuſtom.</hi> Certainly theſe Men muſt believe that Religion conſiſts in the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Perſons, and not in the Doctrine of the Goſpel. I can think no other of them but that they do not know Truth, but by meer human reaſoning, and that they have no manner of Zeal either for this or that Party; but follow that which they find the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for them, and have never minded the Word, which rejects
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:49820:75"/>the <hi>Lukewarm,</hi> and ranks the <hi>Fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> the <hi>Murtherers,</hi> and <hi>Adulterers,</hi> under the ſame Condemnation. Here I am forced to confeſs my own weakneſs in accuſing theirs, and to own that ſometimes I look upon them with pity; at other times with anger; and then again with indifference. But I can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee without horror, the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> from the Faith; the moſt wicked of all Men, the very expreſs Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of him that is the Head of all <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi> Theſe are they who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray their own Brethren, make a Trade of their Revolt, ſcandalize a whole People, and think more of growing rich, than of ſaving their own Souls. Do but give them the Bag, and they will ſide with you as <hi>Judas</hi> did, (who like them) was not ſenſible that his Sale of his Maſter, was the purchaſe of his own deſpair. As they never had a
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:49820:75"/>good will, ſo they neglected to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themſelves, when they made an outward Profeſſion of the True Religion; and they are no ſooner turn'd, but they immediately ſtart up great Diſputants, grow troubleſome with their Queſtions, and ſubtle in maintaining their Change. To which purpoſe they make uſe of all the reaſons in the World, though they know in their Conſcience they have no other for it but the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Judgment, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſs of their Nature, and the difficulty of reconciling their <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Avarice</hi> with the <hi>Reproach</hi> and <hi>Poverty</hi> of JESUS CHRIST: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the Promiſes of Great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and their gracious looks car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I do not know what Charms with them, from which it is hard to defend ones ſelf. On theſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions mean and mercenary Minds ſurrender themſelves, in a manner,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:49820:76"/>without any reſiſtance, and their baſtardly Spirits can hold out no longer, when courted by thoſe who uſed to command them; and when their Maſters turn their Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers. In ſhort, the greateſt part of Men ſeems to be born for Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; neither is there any ſo hard, but they will yield to, nay, and prefer it too before the Liberty of Chriſt, ſo their Chains be but of Gold. They are always ready to pay their Adoration to them that make them rich, or confer Honours upon them; and with the Heathen know no other <hi>Gods</hi> but their <hi>Benefactors.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:49820:76"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p n="40">XL. AMong ſo many bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or ſick Minds; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſo many wilful Blind and vile Slaves of this World, I have been ſeeking for ſome, in whom I might diſcover ſome Purity of Conſcience, and ſome Teſtimony of their Election, and with whom I might joyn my ſelf in that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Communion and Bond of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection that makes them to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable from their Creator and Neighbours. For what Comfort could I reap from thoſe Favourers and Favourites of this World, in whoſe Company a Man is oblig'd, by I don't know what prepoſterous Good Manners, ever to hold his Tongue about Religion; and who either diſcourſe not at all of Divine Matters, or if they do, it is in a
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:49820:77"/>meer human way? What ſweetneſs could I reap from their Friendſhip whoſe heart was not united to mine in what ſhould be the chief end of our Hopes and Deſires? I wiſhed I could diſcern the Children of Heaven, from the Children of the Earth; and the meeting with a <hi>Believer</hi> was to me as if I had ſeen the face of an <hi>Angel.</hi> But amidſt ſo many Men I have often laboured (but in vain) to find out one Man only, though I was not ſo clear ſighted as <hi>Elias,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings,</hi> 19.10, 14, 18. who did not ſee one ſingle perſon in all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though indeed there were a great many. My lot is fallen in an Age where Men are already degenerated from that former Simplicity and new Reformation, and wherein thoſe that bear the Name of <hi>Reformed,</hi> with large ſteps purſue the ſame ways with thoſe who have deſtroy'd
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:49820:77"/>the moſt flouriſhing Churches. I ſaw among them the ſame Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs in Words and Actions, the ſame ſuperfluity in their Dreſs and Habits, and the ſame Luxury, which heretofore ſcandaliz'd <hi>Julian</hi> the Emperor, and confirmed him in his Apoſtacy. <hi>Iniquity was ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed that the Charity of many waxed cold: Mat.</hi> 24.12. And by what appear'd outwardly I could not ſee any difference between the <hi>Falſe</hi> Chriſtians and thoſe that were <hi>True.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="41">XLI. Theſe I could no where better look for, than in the moſt lawful Aſſemblies; but I could not diſcern the Church in the Church it ſelf. She does not ſtand in need of thoſe whoſe Devotion chiefly conſiſts of Geſtures and Wry-faces, who never find a Sermon too long, nor a Communion too frequent, and to whom Religion would ſeem too cold, if it had not ſomething
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:49820:78"/>of the Zeal of Superſtition. She does but too much abound with ſuch as ſerve only to make up a Number, and ſeem to be engaged therein more by their Birth or Chance, than by any deſire or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection they have of improving themſelves in the knowledge of Truth. One would think they only come to ſee the World in a Place from whence the World ſhould in ſome ſort, be baniſhed, where they behave themſelves with ſo little reſpect, that it would be a great miſtake to call them Hypocrites, in whom not the leaſt ſign of Zeal or Devotion is to be obſerved. They aim at nothing elſe but to make a ſhew in the moſt conſpicuous Places; whereas they ſhould return thanks to God that he allows them any in the Company of the Saints; and it ſhould ſuffice them (without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:49820:78"/>to any other advantage) to have only ſo much room there as they need to put both knees to the ground. Some make of the Day of Reſt a day of trouble, and perform the moſt juſt Duty in the World, as a toilfom and tedious Task. Others are ſo abominably wicked and profligate, as to hear Sermons, with no other intent than to find fault with them, and wreſt the meaning, or make a mock of the Preacher. Many cannot reliſh plain, pure, eaſie, and rational Exhortations; and no Truth can move them, unleſs it be preſented to them in a pleaſing Elocution, a thundering Voice, and eloquent Tongue; and unleſs it be adorned with all the Flowers of Rhetorick. They ſlight thoſe things that are plain and obvious, and think that below them, which the common ſort are able to apprehend. You
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:49820:79"/>cannot ſatisfie them, unleſs you undertake ſome high Myſtery, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom the great Deeps, or wire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw ſome difficult Point or other, that only belongs to God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, and the knowledge whereof he has reſerved to himſelf. They have forgotten, That as he who <hi>has choſen the weak things of the World to confound the mighty,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27. was humble, ſo he will have our Knowledge to be modeſt, and not preſumptuous; that he has put his Word into the Mouths of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who yet cannot expreſs it ſo weakly, but that they that love it, will know how to diſcern it from the flaſh and glittering out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of Lie. They have forgot that he doth not willingly employ the skill of ſo many Languages, but to harden thoſe, to whom he has ſo often offer'd his Grace, and they as often rejected it, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:49820:79"/>Error with an obſtinacy, which they will have paſs for ſtrength, and may be call'd the Conſtancy and Virtue of Reprobates. True Believers, in order to their being perſwaded, need not the Miniſtry of Eloquence; which indeed is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom introduced into the Church, but upon the Decay of Faith; and when ſo much Art is uſed for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Men, and ſtirring them up to Piety, 'tis a viſible mark of the hardneſs of their Hearts. Yet the Preachers are oblig'd in compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the itching Ears and nice Palates of their Hearers, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come nice and over-curions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and leave the Simplicity of the Apoſtles to betake themſelves ſometimes to the ſubtleties of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, and at other times to to the lofty Terms of Orators. Cenſure is no longer of uſe in theſe caſes, no more than for the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:49820:80"/>Manners of the Great Men of the World; and many Evils have got ſuch footing in moſt Churches already, that very few can be found who have either courage or ſtrength to remove them. The Saints in our Days have much ado to reſiſt the torrent of the Age, and the Devil makes him ſelf inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to be honoured in the Perſons of the Mighty.</p>
               <p n="42">XLII. I Found therefore no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation but in the Doctrine, yet doubted not but that there were Believers, where I ſaw the Word of Truth was preach'd. But it was ſo much the more difficult for me to know them, becauſe the <hi>Wicked</hi> have all the <hi>Actions</hi> of the <hi>Good,</hi> and the <hi>Good</hi> all the <hi>Infirmities</hi> of the <hi>Wicked.</hi> Very few are found who always take care that their Works ſhould be ſo conformable to the Precepts of the Goſpel, as not to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:49820:80"/>diverted by other Promiſes and to purſue other Hopes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, God calls them in each Sex, Age, and Profeſſion; He invites them to him, that perſecute him; and of his greateſt Foes (when he pleaſes) makes his moſt faithful Friends. Yea, and by a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the cauſes whereof are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable, he in an inſtant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts them who lead an ill Life, and prefers them before thoſe whoſe Manners ſeem to be perfectly good and holy, and who do even boaſt that they have fulfilled the Law. Certainly the moſt Righteous do but fall too often, either through an extraordinary Fear, or a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize of Satan, or by a Trial from God himſelf, who for a while a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandons them to the weakne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of their own Nature, that they may not miſdeem themſelves, nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute that to their own Virtue,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:49820:81"/>which is the meer Product of the Heavenly Grace in them. But with theſe the Gift of God is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the ſtrongeſt; ſo that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Sinful Pleaſures whereby they are over-taken, and the Errors that carry them away, it happens to them as to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal Son; They muſt ſoon or late return to their Father. However 'tis not by any compoſed or demure Looks, nor any peculiar Garb they are to be known: They do not affect to appear otherwiſe than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men, nor recommend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by any extravagant or unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Form: All their Actions have nothing common with thoſe of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites; Their Devotion ſerves not for a Cloak to their Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; nor their Humility for a Mask to their Ambition: They put on no diſguiſe; nor is there any alteration to be ſeen outwardly in
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:49820:81"/>their Countenances, but ſuch as really proceeds from an inward feeling, God affords them of thoſe ſupernatural things which World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings cannot be ſenſible of. When once the Holy Ghoſt has touched them, there always remains in them a certain Character and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion that makes them ſhine in the ſight of the Almighty, as the Stars in the Night, which yet have no other Light but what is commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to them from the Sun. He that made, and is the Searcher of all Hearts does both know them, and make them known to whom he pleaſes. But many there are that ſeem to be Believers, who are not ſo indeed, or at the beſt have but a temporal Faith. Nevertheleſs, if we may be allowed to paſs any Judgment upon it, methinks Men's Converſation ſhews their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:49820:82"/>plain enough. And I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that thoſe who do love God with a true heart, are for the moſt part, taken up with the Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of his Works, and above all, with the Meditation of his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Word: in the reading of which they continually exerciſe themſelves, not out of meer curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, nor to find fault with it; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of a vain deſire of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor as Mercenaries, to teach it to others, and make a Gain of it, but only to inſtruct themſelves, ſeek for Comfort, ſtrengthen their Faith, and aſſure their Hopes. They have it always in their Mouths, or in their Thoughts, and their greateſt trouble is, that they cannot impart it to thoſe who miſtruſt it, and keep themſelves as induſtriouſly from it, as they would from a Snare, who fear it as much as the Singing of Mermaids, and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:49820:82"/>whoſe abominable Wickedneſs make them incompatible with its Purity. A Spirit of diſcerning is a Gift, ſo few are bleſſed with, that none but the true Elect know how or what to chooſe, none but they that are truly Spiritual know how <hi>to try all things, and hold faſt that which is good,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.21. They are not diſturbed that ſo many falſe Prophets, who raſhly aſſume the Name of God; boaſt themſelves to be the Diſpenſers of his Word, make it ſerve their wicked ends, and explain it as the Devil did, when he was ſo daring as to tempt the Son of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as he ſtill does thoſe who make it their profeſſion to follow him.</p>
               <p n="43">XLIII. In ſhort, the Hurries and Intrigues of the World, are none of their Concerns; they ſlight them, and for that reaſon,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:49820:83"/>are ſlighted too; Nay, they are not only vilified and contemned upon this account; but hated and perſecuted, as if their manner of Living, as well as their Belief, was a Reproach to that of others. They do not willingly engage themſelves in any Party, unleſs the Service of God, or the Good of their own Country obliges them thereto: And if they are called to any Office or Dignity, 'tis not in their Nature to canvas, give bribes, or uſe any underhand-dealings to obtain Mens Votes or Favours for it. Neither is it their Practice to encreaſe their Wealth to the prejudice of Faith and Charity. Theſe Common Sayings, <hi>To get an Eſtate, To make one's Fortune, To raiſe one's Family,</hi> are none of their uſual Talk; tho' in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed their Ambition may be ſaid to be greater than that of others, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as no Worldly Grandeur can
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:49820:83"/>ſet bounds to it. They are not ignorant what the lawful uſe of Things is, nor what Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Decency and Neceſſity allow them who are poſſeſſed of Honours and great Places. But they do not underſtand, for whom they labour, who never grow weary of heaping up Riches, who raiſe ſuch high ſtructures, undertake ſo vaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, that they can never expect to live long enough to ſee the end of them. They think no Man can be call'd Judicious or Rational, but he that ſeriouſly applys himſelf to the knowledge of his Supream Good; and they look with pity upon the miſerable Occupations of them that are as much ty'd to the Earth, as if they had no Pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at all to Heaven. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with grief and horror the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence of thoſe, who deny nothing to their Senſes or Appeti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, and
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:49820:84"/>make no other uſe of their Riches and Power, than to commit all manner of crimes, and to tyranize over their Neighbours with the more freedom and impunity. They withdraw themſelves, as far as they can, from the converſation of the Wicked, and as they are no flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, ſo is their company leſs pleaſing to others. They cannot without great reluctancy, be complaiſant to ſuch whoſe Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are diſpleaſing to them, or to give their approbation to ſo many Errors and Vanities. They cannot admire that which God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns, nor afford a pleaſant look to thoſe Objects that grieve their Hearts. But notwithſtanding all the conſtraint and unca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſs they ſuffer in this troubleſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and the great averſion they have for theſe things, yet is their ſeverity always leſs than their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:49820:84"/>Under pretence of forſaking the World, they do not defraud their lawful Heirs, neither do they ſtrive to grow rich by the ruin of others; they know they ſhould be worſe than Publicans, did they not take care of their own Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and that, according to the Divine Rule, <hi>They that will not work muſt not feed,</hi> 2. Theſſ. 3.10. Upon which account, Working Days are no leſs welcome, than the Days of Reſt is Sacred to them. But they are ſo far from minding nothing elſe but their Temporal Concerns, that they will ever and anon cry out with their Maſter, <hi>Lo I come, I delight to do thy will, O my God,</hi> Pſal. 40.9. And though they live, or rather languiſh in this World, as being out of their own Element; though they are, as it were, alone in the midſt of a Multitude, and as <hi>Strangers to their Mothers Children;</hi>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:49820:85"/>though their Purity and Holineſs be accounted Fooliſhneſs, and their Strength look'd upon as Weakneſs in them, yet that does not give them the leaſt trouble; they are very little concerned to ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Evil ſpoken of for well doing,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.17, and to loſe their <hi>Credit,</hi> provided they keep but their <hi>Conſciences.</hi> They know very well that if they would be Men-Pleaſers, they could not be God's Servants; That it is impoſſible to believe in him, and at the ſame time be ſo eager in the purſuit of the glory of the World, which moſt infallibly becomes bitter to them, to whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> begins to be Sweet. They are well aware, that this Life is but a Paſſage, a Place of Trial, or rather a Field of Battle, where ſuch as will not fight ought to expect neither Honour nor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:49820:86"/>
               <p n="44">XLIV. Now, how to reconcile the Learning of ſo many Doctors, with their obduration in this Caſe, I am quite at a loſs: I cannot Imagine how they can think of the Goſpel, and never think of their own Conſcience; I am aſtoniſhed that ſo much Light as they have, ſhould not oblige them to know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and cry out, <hi>Certainly we are in Error; and our Profeſſion is quite contrary to that of</hi> Chriſt <hi>and his Apoſtles. It is Written,</hi> that all thoſe who will live godlily in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> ſhall ſuffer Perſecution; <hi>Where is the Perſecution we ſuffer? We are the Darlings and Favourites of the World; both Princes and People are for us; We enjoy the pleaſures of the Earth, and our lot falls always in the beſt place.</hi> If this be not the Kingdom of this World, pray tell me what is? <q>Shall we caſt into this account the Vows of Poverty,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:49820:86"/>Faſtings, Auſterities, and Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications of ſome of our own Party? But ſo far are they from being blamed, hated, or perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therefore, that they are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured of Men, and ſo receive their reward: And after all, theſe voluntary Afflictions are of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Invention, and of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of thoſe concerning which the Scripture thus expoſtulates with Men, <hi>Who has required theſe things at your hand?</hi> 
                     <bibl>Iſa. 1.12.</bibl>
                  </q> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I am aſtoniſhed that the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees of this Age do not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times reflect upon theſe Matters, ſince Affliction is ſo certainly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex'd to the Profeſſion of True Chriſtianity, that I doubt whether they may be ſaid to have once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be Chriſtians, who were never perſecuted. For if in ſome Countries in the World, the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Heaven, which perhaps
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:49820:86"/>favours the zeal of ſome Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſuffers Religion to flouriſh, and (as the Scripture ſpeaks) <hi>poſſeſs the Gates of her Enemies,</hi> Gen. 22.17. and 24.60; preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Abuſes and Inſolence, that are commonly the Attendants of Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, the Practices of the Devil and his Emiſſaries, are apt to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and corrupt her, and inſpire her with an emulation of Worldly Religions, and a Contempt of her Primitive Simplicity. Would we have the Servants greater than their Maſter, and partake of his Conſolation and Glory, and not of his Sufferings and Patience? No, no, they muſt find Joy in the midſt of Sorrows, and be as a Roſe among thorns; And the ſame muſt happen to them as befell <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who was made greater by his Exile, and whoſe Elevation was from a Dungeon; and as <hi>Job,</hi>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:49820:87"/>whoſe Youth was renew'd through Affliction. They ought with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to look upon it as a ſingular favour, <hi>That unto them it is given in the behalf of Chriſt, not only to believe on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake,</hi> Ph. 1.29. and ſtill think their ſufferings are very ſmall in compariſon of what they hope for. <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable Companions of <hi>Faith;</hi> all three together conſtitute a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, and are the infallible Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters by which he is known. I don't mean that Faith that is obſcure, blind, weak and ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering, which depends upon Birth, Opinion, Cuſtom, and Tradition, which is always doubtful and apt to be ſcandaliz'd at every thing, which does not mortifie the Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, nor forſake the World, is a ſtranger to Self-denial, and ſinks under Perſecutions. I do not mean
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:49820:87"/>that Faith which does not follow <hi>Chriſt</hi> but for its own convenience, and which, of all his Miracles, chiefly eyes that which multiply's the Loaves. But I ſpeak of a Faith that is clear, certain, and conſtant, which proceeds from the Virtue of the Holy Spirit, from the Word of Eternal Life, from Prayer and Humility; which is not acquired but revealed, and which does not enter the hearts of thoſe that have but a Human Faith. I ſpeak of that Faith that rids us of the Cares of tranſitory things, that raviſhes us into an admiration of the Divine Graces, that ſurpaſſes all human diſcourſe and reaſoning, and engages us to glorifie Him who gave it us, <hi>with groans that cannot be uttered,</hi> Rom. 8.26.</p>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:49820:88"/>
               <p>WHICH <hi>Precious Gift</hi> the FATHER of MERCIES vouchſafe to us all through JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST Our Lord.</p>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:49820:88"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
